<Chapter xmlns:i="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.dhammasukha.org/dhammapada">
  <FirstParagraph>1</FirstParagraph>
  <LastParagraph>20</LastParagraph>
  <Nr>1</Nr>
  <Pali>Yamaka Vagga</Pali>
  <Title>The Twin Verses</Title>
  <Verses>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>1</Nr>
          <Txt>Mind is the forerunner of all evil states. Mind is chief; mind made are they. If one speaks or acts with an unwholesome mind, because of that, suffering follows one, even as the wheel follows the hoof of the draft-ox.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Thera Cakkhupala</Title>
        <Txt>
          While residing at the Jetavana monastery in Sāvatthī, the Buddha uttered Verse (1) of this book, with reference to Cakkhupala, a blind thera.
          On one occasion, Thera Cakkhupala came to pay homage to the Buddha at the Jetavana monastery. One night, while pacing up and down in meditation, the thera accidentally stepped on some insects. In the morning, some monks visiting the thera found the dead insects. They thought ill of the thera and reported the matter to the Buddha. The Buddha asked them whether they had seen the thera killing the insects. When they answered in the negative, the Buddha said,"Just as you had not seen him killing, so also he had not seen those living insects. Besides, as the thera had already attained arahatship he could have no intention of killing and so was quite innocent." On being asked why Cakkhupala was blind although he was an arahat, the Buddha told the following story:
          Cakkhupala was a physician in one of his past existences. Once, he had deliberately made a woman patient blind. That woman had promised him to become his slave, together with her children, if her eyes were completely cured. Fearing that she and her children would have to become slaves, she lied to the physician. She told him that her eyes were getting worse when, in fact, they were perfectly cured. The physician knew she was deceiving him, so in revenge, he gave her another ointment, which made her totally blind. As a result of this evil deed the physician lost his eyesight many times in his later existences.
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Evil begets evil</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>2</Nr>
          <Txt>Mind is the forerunner of (all good) states. Mind is chief; mind-made are they. If one speaks or acts with a wholesome mind, because of that, happiness follows one, even as one's shadow that never leaves. </Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Matthakundali</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery in Sāvatthī, the Buddha uttered Verse (2) of this book, with reference to Matthakundali, a young Brahmin. Matthakundali was a young brahmin, whose father, Adinnapubbaka, was very stingy and never gave anything in charity. Even the gold ornaments for his only son were made by himself to save payment for workmanship. When his son fell ill, no physician was consulted, until it was too late. When he realized that his son was dying, he had the youth carried outside on to the verandah, so that people coming to his house would not see his possessions.
          On that morning, the Buddha arising early from his deep meditation of compassion saw, in his Net of Knowledge, Matthakundali lying on the verandah. So when entering Sāvatthī for alms-food with his disciples, the Buddha stood near the door of the brahmin Adinnapubbaka. The Buddha sent forth a ray of light to attract the attention of the youth, who was facing the interior of the house. The youth saw the Buddha; and as he was very weak he could only profess his faith mentally. But that was enough. When he passed away with his heart in devotion to the Buddha he was reborn in the Tavatimsa celestial world.
          From his celestial abode the young Matthakundali, seeing his father mourning over him at the cemetery, appeared to the old man in the likeness of his old self. He told his father about his rebirth in the Tavatimsa world and also urged him to approach and invite the Buddha to a meal. At the house of Adinnapubbaka the question of whether one could or could not be reborn in a celestial world simply by mentally professing profound faith in the Buddha, without giving in charity or observing the moral precepts, was brought up. So the Buddha willed that Matthakundali should appear in person; Matthakundali soon appeared fully decked with celestial ornaments and told them about his rebirth in the Tavatimsa world. Then only, the audience became convinced that the son of the brahmin Adinnapubbaka by simply devoting his mind to the Buddha had attained much glory. </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Good begets good</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>3</Nr>
          <Txt>"He abused me, he beat me, he defeated me, he robbed me", in those who harbour such thoughts hatred is not appeased.</Txt>
        </Par>
        <Par>
          <Nr>4</Nr>
          <Txt>"He abused me, he beat me, he defeated me, he robbed me", in those who do not harbour such thoughts hatred is appeased. </Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Thera Tissa</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery in Sāvatthī, the Buddha uttered Verses (3) and (4) of this book, with reference to Thera Tissa.
          Tissa, son of the Buddha's maternal aunt, was at one time staying with the Buddha. He had become a monk only in his old age, but he posed as a senior monk and was very pleased when visiting monks asked his permission to do some service for him. On the other hand, he failed to perform the duties expected of junior monks; besides, he often quarrelled with the younger monks.
          Should anyone rebuke him on account of his behaviour he would go complaining to the Buddha, weeping, very much dissatisfied and very upset. The others also followed him to the presence of the Buddha. The Buddha told them not to harbour thoughts of enmity, for enmity could only be appeased by not harbouring enmity.
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Retaliation does not lead to peace</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>5</Nr>
          <Txt>Hatred is never overcome by hatred in this world; hatred can only be overcome by love. This is an eternal law. </Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Kalayakkhini</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery in Sāvatthī, the Buddha uttered Verse (5) of this book, with reference to a certain woman who was barren, and her rival.
          Once there lived a householder, whose wife was barren; later he took another wife. The feud started when the elder wife caused abortion of the other one, who eventually died in child birth. In later existences the two were reborn as a hen and a cat; a doe and a leopardess; and finally as the daughter of a nobleman in Sāvatthī and an ogress named Kali. 
          The ogress (Kalayakkhini) was in hot pursuit of the lady with the baby, when the latter learned that the Buddha was nearby, giving a religious discourse at the Jetavana monastery. She fled to him and placed her son at his feet for protection. The ogress was stopped at the door by the guardian spirit of the monastery and was refused admission. She was later called in and both the lady and the ogress were reprimanded by the Buddha. The Buddha told them about their past feuds as rival wives of a common husband, as a cat and a hen, and as a doe and a leopardess. They were made to see that hatred could only cause more hatred, and that it could only cease through friendship, understanding and goodwill.
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Anger is conquered by love</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>6</Nr>
          <Txt>The others know not that in this quarrel we perish; those of them who realize it, have their quarrels calmed thereby. </Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Kosambi Monks</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery in Sāvatthī, the Buddha uttered Verse (6) of this book, with reference to the monks of Kosambi.
          The monks of Kosambi had formed into two groups. One group followed the master of Vinaya and the other followed the teacher of the Dhamma and they were often quarrelling among themselves. Even the Buddha could not stop them from quarrelling; so he left them and spent the vassa, residence period of the rains, all alone in Rakkhita Grove near Palileyyaka forest. There, the elephant Palileyya waited upon the Buddha.
          The lay disciples of Kosambi, on learning the reason for the departure of the Buddha, refused to make offerings to the remaining monks. This made them realize their mistake and reconciliation took place among themselves. Still, the lay disciples would not treat them as respectfully as before, until they owned up their fault to the Buddha.
          But the Buddha was away and it was in the middle of the vassa; so the monks of Kosambi spent the vassa in misery and hardship.
          At the end of the vassa, the Venerable Ananda and five hundred monks approached the Buddha and gave the message from Annathapindika and other lay disciples imploring him to return. In due course the Buddha returned to the Jetavana monastery in Sāvatthī. The monks followed him there, fell down at his feet, and owned up their fault. The Buddha rebuked them for disobeying him. He told them to remember that they must all die some day and therefore, they must stop their quarrels and must not act as if they would never die.
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Quarrels cease through right thought</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>7</Nr>
          <Txt>Whoever lives contemplating pleasant things, with senses unrestrained, in food immoderate, indolent, inactive, him verily Mara overthrows, as the wind (overthrows) a weak tree.</Txt>
        </Par>
        <Par>
          <Nr>8</Nr>
          <Txt>Whoever lives contemplating "the Impurities", with senses restrained, in food moderate, full of faith, full of sustained energy, him Mara overthrows not, as the wind (does not overthrow) a rocky mountain. </Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Thera Mahakala</Title>
        <Txt>While residing in the neighborhood of the town of Setabya, the Buddha uttered Verses (7) and (8) of this book, with reference to Mahakala and his brother Culakala.
          Mahakala and Culakala were two merchant brothers from the town of Setabya. While travelling about with their merchandise on one occasion, they had a chance to listen to a religious discourse given by the Buddha. After hearing the discourse Mahakala asked the Buddha for admission to the Order of the monks. Culakala also joined the Order but with the intention of coming out of the Order and to bring out his brother along with him.
          Mahakala was serious in his ascetic practice at the cemetery (Sosanika dhutinga) and diligently meditated on decay and impermanence. He finally gained Insight and attained arahatship.
          Later, the Buddha and his disciples, including the brothers, happened to be staying in the forest of Simsapa, near Setabya. While staying there, the former wives of Culakala invited the Buddha and his disciples to their house. Culakala himself went ahead to prepare seating arrangements for the Buddha and his disciples. Once there, the former wives of Culakala made him change into lay clothes.
          The next day, the wives of Mahakala invited the Buddha and his disciples to their house hoping to do the same with Mahakala as the wives of Culakala had done to Culakala. After the meal they requested the Buddha to let Mahakala remain to "express appreciation" (anumodana). So the Buddha and the other disciples left.
          Arriving at the village gate the monks expressed their dissatisfaction and apprehension. They were dissatisfied because Mahakala was permitted to stay behind and they were afraid that, like Culakala, his brother, Mahakala, too, would be made to leave the Order by his former wives. To this, the Buddha replied that the two brothers were not alike.
          Culakala indulged in sensual pleasures and was lazy and weak; he was just like a weak tree.
          Mahakala, on the other hand, was diligent, steadfast and strong in his faith of the Buddha, the Dhamma and the Samgha; he was like a mountain of rock.
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>The weak succumb to temptation.</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>9</Nr>
          <Txt>Whoever, unstainless, without self control and truthfulness, should don the yellow robe, is not worthy of it.</Txt>
        </Par>
        <Par>
          <Nr>10</Nr>
          <Txt>He who is purged of all stain, is well-established in morals and endowed with self-control and truthfulness, is indeed worthy of the yellow robe.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Devadatta</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery in Sāvatthī, the Buddha uttered Verses (9) and (10) of this book, with reference to Devadatta.
          Once the two Chief Disciples, the Venerable Sariputta and the Venerable Maha Moggallana, went from Sāvatthī to Rajagaha. There, the people of Rajagaha invited them, with their one thousand followers, to a morning meal. On that occasion someone handed over a piece of cloth, worth one hundred thousand, to the organizers of the alms-giving ceremony. He instructed them to dispose of it and use the proceeds for the ceremony should there be any shortage of funds, or if there were no such shortage, to offer it to anyone of the monks they thought fit. It so happened that there was no shortage of anything and the cloth was to be offered to one of the theras. Since the two Chief Disciples visited Rajagaha only occasionally, the cloth was offered to Devadatta, who was a permanent resident of Rajagaha.
          Devadatta promptly made the cloth into robes and moved about pompously, wearing them. Then, a certain monk from Rajagaha came to Sāvatthī to pay homage to the Buddha, and told him about Devadatta and the robe, made out of cloth worth one hundred thousand. The Buddha then said that it was not the first time that Devadatta was wearing robes that he did not deserve. The Buddha then related the following story.
          Devadatta was an elephant hunter in one of his previous existences. At that time, in a certain forest, there lived a large number of elephants. One day, the hunter noticed that these elephants knelt down to the paccekabuddhas on seeing them. Having observed that, the hunter stole an upper part of a yellow robe and covered his body and hand with it. Then, holding a spear in his hand, he waited for the elephants on their usual route. The elephants came, and taking him for a paccekabuddha fell down on their knees to pay obeisance. They easily fell prey to the hunter. Thus, one by one, he killed the last elephant in the row each day for many days.
          The Bodhisatta (the Buddha-to-be) was then the leader of the herd. Noticing the dwindling number of his followers he decided to investigate and followed his herd at the end of the line. He was alert, and was therefore able to evade the spear. He caught hold of the hunter in his trunk and was about to dash him against the ground, when he saw the yellow robe. Seeing the yellow robe, he desisted and spared the life of the hunter.
          The hunter was rebuked for trying to kill under cover of the yellow robe and for commuting such an act of depravity. The hunter clearly did not deserve to put on the yellow robe.
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>The pure are worthy of the yellow robe</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>11</Nr>
          <Txt>In the unessential we imagine the essential, in the essential we see the unessential, anyone who entertains such wrong thoughts never will realize the truth.</Txt>
        </Par>
        <Par>
          <Nr>12</Nr>
          <Txt>What is essential we regard as essential, what is unessential we regard as unessential, anyone who entertains such right thoughts will realize the truth.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Thera Sariputta</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at Veluvana, the Bamboo Grove monastery in Rajagaha, the Buddha uttered Verses (11) and (12) of this book, with reference to Sanjaya, a former teacher of the Chief Disciples, the Venerable Sariputta and the Venerable Moggallana (formerly Upatissa and Kolita).
          Upatissa and Kolita were two youths from Upatissa and Kolita, two villages near Rajagaha. While looking at a show they realized the insubstantiality of things and they decided to search for the way to liberation. First, they approached Sanjaya. the wandering ascetic at Rajagaha, but they were not satisfied with his teachings. So they went all over Jambudipa and came back to their native place, after searching for, but not finding the true dhamma. At this point they came to an understanding that one who found the true dhamma should inform the other.
          One day, Upatissa came across Thera Assaji and learned from him the substance of the dhamma. The thera uttered the verse beginning with "Ye dhamma hetuppabhava", meaning, "those phenomena which proceed from a cause". Listening to the verse, Upatissa became established in the Sotapatti Magga and Phala. Then, as promised, he went to his friend Kolita, explained to him that he, Upatissa, had attained the state of Deathlessness and repeated the verse to his friend. Kolita also become established in Sotapatti Fruition at the end of the verse. They both remembered their former teacher and so went to Sanjaya and said to him, "We have found one who could point out the Path to Deathlesseness; the Buddha has appeared in the world; the Dhamma has appeared; the Sangha has appeared... Come, let us go to the Teacher." They had hoped that their former teacher would go along with them to the Buddha and by listening to the discourses he, too, would come to realize Magga and Phala. But Sanjaya refused.
          So Upatissa and Kolita, with two hundred and fifty followers, went to the Buddha, at Veluvana. There, they were initiated and admitted into the Order as monks. Upatissa as son of Rupasari became known as Thera Sariputta; Kolita as son of Moggali became known as Thera Maha Moggallana. On the seventh day after the initiation Maha Moggallana attained Arahatship. Thera Sariputta achieved the same a fortnight after initiation. On that day, the Buddha made them his two Chief Disciples (Agga-Savaka).
          The two Chief Disciples then related to the Buddha how they went to the Giragga festival, the meeting with Thera Assaji and their attainment of Sotapatti Fruition. They also told the Buddha about their former teacher Sanjaya, who refused to accompany them. Sanjaya had said, "Having been a teacher to so many pupils, for me to become his pupil would be like a jar turning into a drinking cup. Besides, only few people are wise and the majority are foolish; let the wise go to the wise Gotama, the foolish would still come to me. Go your way, my pupils."
          Thus, as the Buddha pointed out, Sanjaya's false pride was preventing him from seeing truth as truth; he was seeing untruth as truth and would never arrive at the real truth.
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Right view leads to the truth</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>13</Nr>
          <Txt>Even as rain penetrates as ill-thatched house, so does lust penetrate an undeveloped mind.</Txt>
        </Par>
        <Par>
          <Nr>14</Nr>
          <Txt>Even as rain does not penetrate a well-thatched house, so does lust not penetrate a well-developed mind.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Thera Nanda</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery in Sāvatthī, the Buddha uttered Verses (13) and (14) of this book, with reference to Thera Nanda, a cousin of the Buddha.
          Once the Buddha was residing at the Veluvana monastery in Rajagaha when his father King Suddhodana repeatedly sent messengers to the Buddha requesting him to visit the city of Kapilavatthu. Accordingly, the Buddha made the journey in the company of twenty thousand arahats. On arrival at Kapilavatthu he related the Vessantara Jataka to the assembly of his relatives. On the second day, he entered the city, where by reciting the verse beginning with "Uttitthe Nappamajjeyya ..." (i.e., One should arise and should not be unmindful ...) he caused his father to be established in Sotapatti Fruition. On arrival at the palace, the Buddha recited another verse beginning with "Dhammam care sucaritam ..." (i.e., One should practise the Dhamma...) and established the king in Sakadagami Fruition. After the meal he narrated the Candakinnari Jataka, with reference to the virtues of Rahula's mother.
          On the third day, there was the marriage ceremony of Prince Nanda, a cousin of the Buddha. The Buddha went there for alms and handed over the alms bowl to Prince Nanda. The Buddha then departed without taking back the bowl. So the prince, holding the bowl, had to follow the Buddha. The bride, Princess Janapadakalyani, seeing the prince following the Buddha rushed forth and cried out to the prince to come back soon. At the monastery, the prince was admitted into the Order as a monk.
          Later, the Buddha moved into the monastery built by Anathapindika, at Jeta Park in Sāvatthī. While residing there Nanda was discontented and half-hearted and found little pleasure in the life of a monk. He wanted to return to the life of a householder because he kept on remembering the words of Princess Janapadakalyani, imploring him to return soon.
          Knowing this, the Buddha, by supernormal power, showed Nanda, the beautiful female devas of the Tavatimsa world who were far prettier than Princess Janapadakalyani. He promised to get them for Nanda, if the latter strove hard in the practice of the Dhamma. Other monks ridiculed Nanda by saying that he was like a hireling who practised the Dhamma for the sake of beautiful women, etc. Nanda felt very much tormented and ashamed. So, in seclusion, he tried very hard in the practice of the Dhamma and eventually attained arahatship. As an arahat his mind was totally released from all attachments, and the Buddha was also released from his promise to Nanda. All this had been foreseen by the Buddha right from the very beginning.
          Other monks, having known that Nanda was not happy in the life of a monk, again asked him how he was faring. When he answered that he had no more attachments to the life of a householder, they thought Nanda was not speaking the truth. So they informed the Buddha about the matter, at the same time expressing their doubts. The Buddha then explained to them that, previously, the nature of Nanda was like that of an ill-roofed house, but now, it had grown to be like a well-roofed one.
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Lust is in the heart of the undeveloped</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>15</Nr>
          <Txt>Here he grieves, hereafter he grieves. In both states the evil-doer grieves. He grieves, he is afflicted, perceiving the impurity of his own deeds.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Cundasukarika</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Veluvana monastery in Rajagaha, the Buddha uttered Verse (15) of this book, with reference to Cunda, the pork-butcher.
          Once, in a village not far away from the Veluvana monastery, there lived a very cruel and hard-hearted pork-butcher, by the name of Cunda.
          Cunda was a pork-butcher for over fifty-five years; all this time he had not done a single meritorious deed. Before he died, he was in such great pain and agony that he was grunting and squealing and kept on moving about on his hands and knees like a pig for seven whole days.
          In fact, even before he died, he was suffering as if he were in Niraya. On the seventh day, the pork-butcher died and was reborn in Avici Niraya. Thus, the evil-doer must always suffer for the evil deeds done by him; he suffers in this world as well as in the next.
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Evil-doers suffer here and hereafter</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>16</Nr>
          <Txt>Here one develops a mind that rejoices now, and in the future one rejoices. In both states the well-doer rejoices. One who rejoices a lot will be able to see the purity of their own deeds, speech and thoughts.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Dhammika Upasaka</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery in Sāvatthī, the Buddha uttered Verse (16) of this book, with reference to Dhammika, a lay disciple.
          Once there lived in Sāvatthī, a lay disciple by the name of Dhammika, who was virtuous and very fond of giving in charity. He generously offered food and other requisites to the monks regularly and also on special occasions. He was, in fact, the leader of five hundred virtuous lay disciples of the Buddha who lived in Sāvatthī.
          Dhammika had seven sons and seven daughters and all of them, like their father, were virtuous and devoted to charity. When Dhammika was very ill and was on his death-bed he made a request to the Samgha to come to him and recite the sacred texts by his bedside.
          While the monks were reciting the Maha satipatthana Sutta, six decorated chariots from six celestial worlds arrived to invite him to their respective worlds. Dhammika told them to wait for a while for fear of interrupting the recitation of the Sutta. The monks, thinking that they were being asked to stop, stopped and left the place.
          A little while later, Dhammika told his children about the six decorated chariots waiting for him. Then and there he decided to choose the chariot from the Tusita world and asked one of his children to throw a garland on to it. Then he passed away and was reborn in the Tusita world. Thus, the virtuous man rejoices in this world as well as in the next.
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Happy are the well-doers</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>17</Nr>
          <Txt>Here he suffers, hereafter he suffers. In both states the evil-doer suffers. "Evil have I done" (thinking thus), he suffers. Furthermore, he suffers, having gone to a woeful state. </Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Devadatta</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery in Sāvatthī, the Buddha uttered Verse (17) of this book, with reference to Devadatta.
          Devadatta was at one time residing with the Buddha in Kosambi. While staying there he realized that the Buddha was receiving much respect and honour as well as offerings. He envied the Buddha and aspired to head the Order of the monks. One day, while the Buddha was preaching at the Veluvana monastery in Rajagaha, he approached the Buddha and on the ground that the Buddha was getting old, he suggested that the Order be entrusted to his care. The Buddha rejected his offer and rebuked him, saying that he was a swallower of other people's spittle. The Buddha next asked the Samgha to carry out an act of proclamation (Pakasaniya kamma) regarding Devadatta.
          Devadatta felt aggrieved and vowed vengeance against the Buddha. Three times, he attempted to kill the Buddha: first, by employing some archers; secondly, by climbing up the Gijjhakuta hill and rolling down a big piece of rock on to the Buddha; and thirdly, by causing the elephant Nalagiri to attack the Buddha.
          The hired assassins returned after being established in Sotapatti Fruition, without harming the Buddha. The big piece of rock rolled down by Devadatta hurt the big toe of the Buddha just a little, and when the Nalagiri elephant rushed at the Buddha, it was made docile by the Buddha. Thus Devadatta failed to kill the Buddha, and he tried another tactic.
          He tried to break up the Order of the monks by taking away some newly admitted monks with him to Gayasisa; however, most of them were brought back by Thera Sariputta and Thera Maha Moggallana.
          Later, Devadatta fell ill. He had been ill for nine months when he asked his pupils to take him to the Buddha, and subsequently made the trip to the Jetavana monastery. Hearing that Devadatta was coming, the Buddha told his disciples that Devadatta would never get the opportunity to see him.
          When Devadatta and his party reached the pond in the Jetavana monastery compound the carriers put down the couch on the bank of the pond and went to take a bath. Devadatta also rose from his couch and placed both his feet on the ground. Immediately, his feet sank into the earth and he was gradually swallowed up, Devadatta did not have the opportunity to see the Buddha because of the wicked deeds he had done to the Buddha. After his death, he was reborn in Avici Niraya, a place of intense and continuous torment.
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>The evil-doer laments here and hereafter</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>18</Nr>
          <Txt>When one is happy now, they will be happy in the future. In both states the well-doer is happy. Thinking "I have done good in the past" one becomes happy and will easily experience a blissful state of mind.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Sumanadevi</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery in Sāvatthī, the Buddha uttered Verse (18) of this book, with reference to Sumanadevi, the youngest daughter of Anathapindika.
          In Sāvatthī, at the house of Anathapindika and the house of Visakha, two thousand monks were served with food daily. At the house of Visakha, the offering of alms-food was supervised by her granddaughter.
          At the house of Anathapindika, the supervision was done, first by the eldest daughter, next by the second daughter and finally by Sumanadevi, the youngest daughter. The two elder sisters attained Sotapatti Fruition by listening to the Dhamma, while serving food to the monks. Sumanadevi did even better and she attained Sakadagami Fruition.
          Later, Sumanadevi fell ill and on her death-bed she asked for her father. Her father came, and she addressed her father as "younger brother" (Kanittha bhatika) and passed away soon after. Her form of address kept her father wondering and made him uneasy and depressed, thinking that his daughter was delirious and not in her right senses at the time of her death. So, he approached the Buddha and reported to him about his daughter, Sumanadevi. Then the Buddha told the noble rich man that his daughter was in her right senses and fully self-possessed at the time of her passing away.
          The Buddha also explained that Sumanadevi had addressed her father as "younger brother" because her attainment of Magga and Phala was higher than that of her father's. She was a Sakadagam whereas her father was only a Sotapanna.
          Anathapindika was also told that Sumanadevi was reborn in the Tusita deva world.
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Happy are the righteous</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>19</Nr>
          <Txt>Though a person recites sacred texts, but doesn’t act accordingly, that heedless person is like a cowherd who counts others’ cows. They have no share in the fruits of the holy life.</Txt>
        </Par>
        <Par>
          <Nr>20</Nr>
          <Txt>Though a person recites the sacred texts very little, but acts in accordance with the teaching, they give up lust, hatred and delusion. They truly know what is good and this leads to a mind that is free from suffering. They cling to nothing here and in the future. In this way, one shares the fruits of the holy life.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Two Friends</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verses (19) and (20) of this book, with reference to two monks who were friends.
          Once there were two friends of noble family, two monks from Sāvatthī. One of them learned the Tipitaka and was very proficient in reciting and preaching the sacred texts. He taught five hundred monks and became the instructor of eighteen groups of monks.The other monk striving diligently and ardently in the course of Insight Meditation attained arahatship together with Analytical Insight.
          On one occasion, when the second monk came to pay homage to the Buddha, at the Jetavana monastery, the two monks met. The master of the Tipitaka did not realize that the other had already become an arahat. He looked down on the other, thinking that this old monk knew very little of the sacred texts, not even one out of the five Nikayas or one out of the three Pitakas. So he thought of putting questions to the other, and thus embarass him. The Buddha knew about his unkind intention and he also knew that as a result of giving trouble to such a noble disciple of his, the learned monk would be reborn in a lower world.
          So, out of compassion, the Buddha visited the two monks to prevent the scholar from questioning the other monk. The Buddha himself did the questioning. He put questions on jhanas and maggas to the master of the Tipitaka; but he could not answer them because he had not practised what he had taught. The other monk, having practised the Dhamma and having attained arahatship, could answer all the questions. The Buddha praised the one who practised the Dhamma (i.e., a vipassaka), but not a single word of praise was spoken for the learned scholar (i.e., a ganthika).
          The resident disciples could not understand why the Buddha had words of praise for the old monk and not for their learned teacher. So, the Buddha explained the matter to them. The scholar who knows a great deal but does not practise in accordance with the Dhamma is like a cowherd, who looks after the cows for wages, while the one who practises in accordance with the Dhamrna is like the owner who enjoys the five kinds of produce of the cows. Thus, the scholar enjoys only the services rendered to him by his pupils but not the benefits of Magga-phala. 
          The other monk, though he knows little and recites only a little of the sacred texts, having clearly comprehended the essence of the Dhamma and having practised diligently and strenuously, is an 'anudhammacari', who has eradicated passion, ill will and ignorance. His mind being totally freed from moral delilements and from all attachments to this world as well as to the next, he truly shares the benefits of Magga-phala.
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Learning without practice is of no worth</Summary>
    </Verse>
  </Verses>
</Chapter>
