<Chapter xmlns:i="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.dhammasukha.org/dhammapada">
  <FirstParagraph>129</FirstParagraph>
  <LastParagraph>145</LastParagraph>
  <Nr>10</Nr>
  <Pali>Daṇóa Vagga</Pali>
  <Title>The Rod Or Punishment</Title>
  <Verses>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>129</Nr>
	  <Txt>All tremble at the rod. All fear death. Comparing others with oneself, one should neither strike nor cause to strike. </Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>a Group of Six Monks</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Javana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (129) of this book, with reference to a group of six monks (chabbaggi) who picked a quarrel with another group comprising seventeen monks.
    Once seventeen monks were cleaning up a building in the Jetavana monastery-complex with the intention of occupying it, when another group comprising six monks arrived on the scene.
    The group of six said to the first group, "We are senior to you, so you had better give way to us; we will take this place." The group of seventeen did not give in, so the chabbaggis beat up the other group who cried out in pain.
    The Buddha learning about this reprimanded them and laid down the disciplinary rule forbidding monks to beat others.
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Kill not</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>130</Nr>
	  <Txt>All tremble at the rod. Life is dear to all. Comparing others with oneself, one should neither strike nor cause to strike.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>a Group of Six Monks</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (130) of this book, with reference to a group of six monks.
    After coming to blows the first time, the same two groups of monks quarrelled again over the same building. As the rule prohibiting beating others had already been laid down, the group of six threatened the other group with upraised hands. The group of seventeen, who were junior to the chabbaggis, cried out in fright. 
    The Buddha hearing about this laid down the disciplinary rule forbidding the raising of hands in threat.
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Life is dear to all</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>131</Nr>
	  <Txt>Whoever, seeking his own happiness, harms with the rod other pleasure-loving beings experiences no happiness hereafter.</Txt>
	</Par>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>132</Nr>
	  <Txt>Whoever, seeking his own happiness, harms not with the rod other pleasure-loving beings, experiences happiness hereafter.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Many Youths</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verses (131) and (132) of this book, with reference to a number of youths.
    Once, the Buddha was out on an alms-round at Sāvatthī when he came across a number of youths beating a snake with sticks. When questioned, the youths answered that they were beating the snake because they were afraid that the snake might bite them.
    To them the Buddha said, "If you do not want to be harmed, you should also not harm others: if you harm others, you will not find happiness in your next existence."
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Molest none</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>133</Nr>
	  <Txt>Speak not harshly to anyone. Those thus addressed will retort. Painful, indeed, is vindictive speech. Blows in exchange may bruise you.</Txt>
	</Par>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>134</Nr>
	  <Txt>If, like a cracked gong, you silence yourself, you have already attained Nibbāna: no vindictiveness will be found in you.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Thera Kondadhana</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verses (133) and (134) of this book, with reference to Thera Kondadhana.
Since the day Kondadhana was admitted to the Order, the image of a female was always following him. This image was seen by others, but Kondadhana himself did not see it and so did not know about it.
When he was out on an alms-round, people would offer two spoonfuls to him, saying, "This is for you, Venerable Sir, and this is for your female companion." Seeing the monk going about with a woman, people went to King Pasenadi of Kosala and reported about the monk and the woman. They said to the king, "O king! Drive out the monk, who is lacking in moral virtues, from your kingdom." So the king went to the monastery where that monk was staying and surrounded it with his men.
Hearing noises and voices, the monks came out and stood at the door, and the image also was there not far from the monk. Knowing that the king had come, the monk went into the room to wait for him. When the king entered the room, the image was not there. The king asked the monk where the woman was and he replied that he saw no woman. The king wanted to make sure and he asked the monk to leave the room for a while. The monk left the room, but when the king looked out, again he saw the woman near the monk. But when the monk came back to the room the woman was nowhere to be found. The king concluded that the woman was not real and so the monk must be innocent. He therefore invited the monk to come to the palace every day for alms-food.
When other monks heard about this, they were puzzled and said to the monk, "O monk with no morals! Now that the king, instead of driving you out of his kingdom, has invited you for alms-food, you are doomed!" The monk on his part retorted, "Only you are the ones without morals; only you are doomed because you are the ones who go about with women!"
The monks then reported the matter to the Buddha. The Buddha sent for Kodadadhana and said to him, "My son, did you see any woman with the other monks that you have talked to them thus? You have not seen any woman with them as they have seen one with you. I see that you do not realize that you have been cursed on account of an evil deed done by you in a past existence. Now listen, I shall explain to you why you have an image of a woman following you about.
"You were a deva in your last existence. During that time, there were two monks who were very much attached to each other. But you tried to create trouble between the two, by assuming the appearance of a woman and following one of the monks. For that evil deed you are now being followed by the image of a woman. So, my son, in future do not argue with other monks any more; keep silent like a gong with the rim broken off and you will realize Nibbāna."
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Speak not harshly</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>135</Nr>
	  <Txt>As with a staff the herdsmen drives his kine to pasture, even so do old age and death drive out the lives of beings.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Some Ladies Observing the Moral Precepts</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Pubbarama monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (135) of this book, with reference to five hundred ladies.
Once, five hundred ladies from Sāvatthī came to the Pubbarama monastery to keep the Uposatha Sila vows. The donor of the monastery, the well-renowned Visakha, asked different age groups of ladies why they had come to keep the sabbath. She got different answers from different age groups for they had come to the monastery for different reasons. The old ladies came to the monastery to keep the sabbath because they hoped to gain the riches and glories of the devas in their next existence; the middle-aged ladies had come to the monastery because they did not want to stay under the same roof with the mistresses of their respective husbands. The young married ladies had come because they wanted their first born to be a son, and the young unmarried ladies had come because they wanted to get married to good husbands.
Having had these answers, Visakha took all the ladies to the Buddha. When she told the Buddha about the various answers of the different age groups of ladies, the Buddha said, "Visakha! birth, ageing and death are always actively working in beings; because one is born, one is subject to ageing and decay, and finally to death. Yet, they do not wish to strive for liberation from the round of existences (samsara); they still wish to linger in samsara"
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Decay and death are universal</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>136</Nr>
	  <Txt>So, when a fool does wrong deeds, he does not realize (their evil nature); by his own deeds the stupid man is tormented, like one burnt by fire.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>the Boa Constrictor Peta</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (136) of this book, with reference to a boa constrictor peta*.
Once, as Thera Maha Moggallana was coming down the Gijjhakuta hill with Thera Lakkhana he saw a boa constrictor peta and smiled, but he did not say anything. When they were back at the Jetavana monastery, Thera Maha Moggallana told Lakkhana, in the presence of the Buddha about the boa constrictor peta, with its long body burning in flames. The Buddha also said he himself had also seen that very peta soon after he had attained Buddhahood, but that he did not say anything about it because people might not believe him and thus they would be doing a great wrong to the Buddha. So out of compassion for these beings, the Buddha had kept silent. Then he continued, "Now that I have a witness in Moggallana, I will tell you about this boa constrictor peta. This peta was a thief during the time of Kassapa Buddha. As a thief and a cruel-hearted man, he had set fire to the house of a rich man seven times. And not satisfied with that, he also set fire to the perfumed hall donated by the same rich man to Kassapa Buddha, while Kassapa Buddha was out on an alms-round. As a result of those evil deeds he had suffered for a long time in niraya. Now, while serving out his term of suffering as a peta, he is being burnt with sparks of flames going up and down the length of his body. Monks, fools when doing evil deeds do not know them as being evil; but they cannot escape the evil consequences"
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>You get what you give</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>137</Nr>
	  <Txt>He who with the rod harms the rodless and harmless, soon will come to one of these states:-</Txt>
	</Par>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>138</Nr>
	  <Txt>He will be subject to acute pain, disaster, bodily injury, or even grievous sickness, or loss of mind, or oppression by the king, or heavy accusation, or loss of relatives, or destruction of wealth, or ravaging fire that will burn his house. Upon the dissolution of the body such unwise man will be born in hell.</Txt>
	</Par>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>139</Nr>
	  <Txt>He will be subject to acute pain, disaster, bodily injury, or even grievous sickness, or loss of mind, or oppression by the king, or heavy accusation, or loss of relatives, or destruction of wealth, or ravaging fire that will burn his house. Upon the dissolution of the body such unwise man will be born in hell.</Txt>
	</Par>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>140</Nr>
	  <Txt>He will be subject to acute pain, disaster, bodily injury, or even grievous sickness, or loss of mind, or oppression by the king, or heavy accusation, or loss of relatives, or destruction of wealth, or ravaging fire that will burn his house. Upon the dissolution of the body such unwise man will be born in hell.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Thera Maha Moggallana</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verses (137), (138), (139) and (140) of this book, with reference to Thera Maha Moggallana.
Once, the Nigantha ascetics planned to kill Thera Maha Moggallana because they thought that by doing away with Thera Maha Moggallana the fame and fortune of the Buddha would also be diminished. So they hired some assassins to kill Thera Maha Moggallana who was staying at Kalasila near Rajagaha at that time. The assassins surrounded the monastery; but Thera Maha Moggallana, with his supernormal power, got away first through a key hole, and for the second time through the roof. Thus, they could not get hold of the Thera for two whole months. When the assassins again surrounded the monastery during the third month, Thera Maha Moggallana, recollecting that he had yet to pay for the evil deeds done by him during one of his past existences, did not exercise his supernormal power. So he was caught and the assassins beat him up until all his bones were utterly broken. After that, they left his body in a bush, thinking that he had passed away. But the Thera, through his jhanic power, revived himself and went to see the Buddha at the Jetavana monastery. When he informed the Buddha that he would soon realize pariNibbāna at Kalasila, near Rajagaha, the Buddha told him to go only after expounding the Dhamma to the congregation of monks, as that would be the last time they would see him. So, Thera Maha Moggallana expounded the Dhamma and left after paying obeisance seven times to the Buddha.
The news of the passing away of Thera Maha Moggallana at the hands of assassins spread like wild fire. King Ajatasattu ordered his men to investigate and get hold of the culprits. The assassins were caught and they were burnt to death. The monks felt very sorrowful over the death of Thera Maha Moggallana, and could not understand why such a personage like Thera Maha Moggallana should die at the hands of assassins. To them the Buddha said, "Monks! Considering that Moggallana had lived a noble life in this existence, he should not have met with such a death. But in one of his past existences, he had done a great wrong to his own parents, who were both blind. In the beginning, he was a very dutiful son, but after his marriage, his wife began to make trouble and she suggested that he should get rid of his parents. He took his blind parents in a cart into a forest, and there he killed them by beating them and making them believe that it was some thief who was beating them. For that evil deed he suffered in niraya for a long time; and in this existence, his last, he has died at the hands of assassins. Indeed, by doing wrong to those who should not be wronged, one is sure to suffer for it."
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Be kind</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>141</Nr>
	  <Txt>Not wandering naked, nor matted locks, nor filth, nor fasting, nor lying on the ground, nor dust, nor ashes, nor striving squatting on the heels, can purify a mortal who has not overcome doubts. </Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Monk Bahubhandika</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (141) of this book, with reference to Bahubhandika, a monk with many possessions.
Once there was a rich man in Sāvatthī. After the death of his wife, he decided to become a monk. But before he entered the Order, he built a monastery, which included a kitchen and a store room. He also brought his own furniture, utensils and a large stock of rice, oil, butter and other provisions. Whatever dishes he wanted was cooked for him by his servants. Thus, even as a monk he was living in comfort, and because he had so many things with him, he was known as 'Bahubhandika.' One day, other monks took him to the Buddha, and in his presence told the Buddha about the many things he had brought along with him to the monastery, and also how he was still leading the luxurious life of a rich man. So, the Buddha said to Bahubhandika, "My son, I have been teaching all of you to live an austere life; why have you brought so much property with you?" When reprimanded even this much, that monk lost his temper and said angrily, "Indeed, Venerable Sir! I will now live as you wish me to." So saying, he cast off his upper robe.
Seeing him thus, the Buddha said to him, "My son, in your last existence you were an ogre; even as an ogre you had a sense of shame and a sense of fear to do evil. Now that you are a monk in my Teaching, why do you have to throw away the sense of shame, and the sense of fear to do evil?" When he heard those words, the monk realized his mistake; his sense of shame and fear to do evil returned, and he respectfully paid obeisance to the Buddha and asked that he should be pardoned. The Buddha then said to him,"Standing there without your upper robe is not proper; just discarding your robe etc., does not maker you an austere monk; a monk must also discard his doubt."
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>External penances cannot purify a person</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>142</Nr>
	  <Txt>Though gaily decked, if he should live in peace, (with passions) subdued, (and senses) controlled, certain (of the four Paths of Sainthood), perfectly pure, laying aside the rod (in his relations) towards all living beings, a Brāhmaṇa indeed is he, an ascetic is he, a monk is he. </Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Santati the Minister</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (142) of this book, with reference to Santati, the minister of King Pasenadi of Kosala.
On one occasion, Santati the minister returned after suppressing a rebellion on the border. King Pasenadi was so pleased with him that he honoured the minister with the gift of the riches and glory of a ruler together with a dancing girl to entertain him for seven days. For seven days, the king's minister enjoyed himself to his heart's content, getting intoxicated with drink and infatuated with the young dancer. On the seventh day, riding the ornamented royal elephant, he went down to the riverside for a bath. On the way, he met the Buddha going on an alms-round, and being drunk, he just bowed casually, as a sign of respect to the Buddha. The Buddha smiled, and Ananda asked the Buddha why he smiled. So, the Buddha said to Ananda, "Ananda, this minister will come to see me this very day and after I have given him a short discourse will become an arahat. Soon after becoming an arahat he will realize pariNibbāna."
Santati and his party spent the whole day at the riverside, bathing, eating, drinking and thus thoroughly enjoying themselves. In the evening the minister and his party went to the garden to have more drinks and to be entertained by the dancer. The dancer, on her part, tried her best to entertain the minister. For the whole week she was living on reduced diet to keep herself trim. While dancing, she suffered a severe stroke and collapsed, and at that instant she died with her eyes and mouth wide open. The minister was shocked and deeply distressed. In agony, he tried to think of a refuge and remembered the Buddha. He went to the Buddha, accompanied by his followers, and related to him about the grief and anguish he suffered on account of the sudden death of the dancer. He then said to the Buddha, "Venerable Sir! Please help me get over my sorrow; be my refuge, and let me have the peace of mind." To him the Buddha replied, "Rest assured my son, you have come to one, who could help you, One who could be a constant solace to you and who will be your refuge. The tears you have shed due to the death of this dancer throughout the round of rebirths is more than the waters of all the oceans." The Buddha then instructed the minister in verse. The meaning of the verse is as follows.
"In the past there has been in you clinging (upadana) due to craving; get rid of it. In future, do not let such clinging occur in you. Do not also harbour any clinging in the present; by not having any clinging, craving and passion will be calmed in you and you will realize Nibbāna."
After hearing the verse, the minister attained arahatship. Then, realizing that his life span was at an end, he said to the Buddha, "Venerable Sir! Let me now realize pariNibbāna, for my time has come." The Buddha consenting, Santati rose to a height of seven toddy-palms into the sky and there, while meditating on the element of fire (tejo kasina), he passed away realizing pariNibbāna. His body went up in flames, his blood and flesh burnt up and the bone relics (dhatu) fell through the sky and dropped on the clean piece of cloth which was spread by the monks as instructed by the Buddha.
At the congregation, the monks asked the Buddha, "Venerable Sir! The minister had realized pariNibbāna dressed in full regalia; is he a samana on a brāhmaṇa?" To them, the Buddha replied "Monks! My son can be called both a samana and a brāhmaṇa."
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Do not judge a book by its cover</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>143</Nr>
	  <Txt>(Rarely) is found in this world anyone who, restrained by modesty, avoids reproach, as a thorough-bred horse (avoids) the whip. </Txt>
	</Par>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>144</Nr>
	  <Txt>Like a thorough-bred horse touched by the whip, even so be strenuous and zealous. By confidence, by virtue, by effort, by collectedness, by investigation of the Truth, by being endowed with knowledge and conduct, and by being mindful, get rid of this great suffering.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Thera Pilotikatissa</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verses (143) and (144) of this book, with reference to Thera Pilotikatissa.
Once, Thera Ananda saw a shabbily dressed youth going round begging for food; he felt pity for the youth and made him a samanera. The young samanera left his old clothes and his begging plate on the fork of a tree. When he became a monk he was known as Pilotikatissa. As a monk, he did not have to worry about food and clothing as he was in affluent circumstances. Yet, sometimes he did not feel happy in his life as a monk and thought of going back to the life of a lay man. Whenever he had this feeling, he would go back to that tree where he had left his old clothes and his plate. There, at the foot of the tree, he would put this question to himself, "Oh shameless one! Do you want to leave the place where you are fed well and dressed well? Do you still want to put on these shabby clothes and go begging again with this old plate in your hand?" Thus, he would rebuke himself, and after calming down, he would go back to the monastery.
After two or three days, again, he felt like leaving the monastic life of a monk, and again, he went to the tree where he kept his old clothes and his plate. After asking himself the same old question and having been reminded of the wretchedness of his old life, he returned to the monastery. This was repeated many times. When other monks asked him why he often went to the tree where he kept his old clothes and his plate, he told them that he went to see his teacher.* Thus keeping his mind on his old clothes as the subject of meditation, he came to realize the true nature of the aggregates of the khandhas (i.e., anicca, dukkha, anatta), and eventually he became an arahat. Then, he stopped going to the tree. Other monks noticing that Pilotikatissa had stopped going to the tree where he kept his old clothes and his plate asked him, "Why don't you go to your teacher any more?" To them, he answered, "When I had the need, I had to go to him; but there is no need for me to go to him now." When the monks heard his reply, they took him to see the Buddha. When they came to his presence they said, "Venerable Sir! This monk claims that he has attained arahatship; he must be telling lies." But the Buddha refuted them, and said, "Monks! Pilotikatissa is not telling lies, he speaks the truth. Though he had relationship with his teacher previously, now he has no relationship whatsoever with his teacher. Thera Pilotikatissa has instructed himself to differentiate right and wrong causes and to discern the true nature of things. He has now become an arahat, and so there is no further connection between him and his teacher."
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>The modest are rare in this world</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>145</Nr>
	  <Txt>Irrigators lead the waters. Fletchers bend the shafts. Carpenters bend the wood. The virtuous control themselves. </Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Samanera* Sukha</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (145) of this book, with reference to a samanera named Sukha.
Sukha was made a samanera at the age of seven years by Thera Sariputta. On the eighth day after being made a samanera he followed Thera Sariputta on his alms-round. While doing the round they came across some farmers irrigating their fields, some fletchers straightening their arrows and some carpenters making things like cart-wheels, etc. Seeing these, he asked Thera Sariputta whether these inanimate things could be guided to where one wished or be made into things one wished to make, and the thera answered him in the affirmative. The young samanera then pondered that if that were so, there could be no reason why a person could not tame his mind and practise Tranquillity and Insight Meditation.
So, he asked permission from the thera to return to the monastery. There, he shut himself up in his room and practised meditation in solitude, Sakka and the devas also helped him in his practice by keeping the monastery very quiet. That same day, the eighth day after his becoming a samanera, Sukha attained arahatship. In connection with this, the Buddha said to the congregation of monks, "When a person earnestly practises the Dhamma, even Sakka and the devas give protection and help. I myself have kept Sariputta at the entrance so that Sukha should not be disturbed. The samanera, having seen the farmers irrigating their fields, the fletchers straightening their arrows and the carpenters making cart-wheels and other things, trains his mind and practises the Dhamma. Thus, he has now become an arahat."
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>The good control themselves</Summary>
    </Verse>
  </Verses>
</Chapter>
