<Chapter xmlns:i="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.dhammasukha.org/dhammapada">
  <FirstParagraph>360</FirstParagraph>
  <LastParagraph>382</LastParagraph>
  <Nr>25</Nr>
  <Pali>Monk Vagga</Pali>
  <Title>The Monk Or The Mendicant</Title>
  <Verses>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>360</Nr>
	  <Txt>Good is restraint in the eye; good is restraint in the ear; good is restraint in the nose; good is restraint in the tongue.</Txt>
	</Par>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>361</Nr>
	  <Txt>Good is restraint in deed; good is restraint in speech; good is restraint in mind; good is restraint in everything. The monk, restrained at all points, is freed from sorrow.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Five Monks</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verses (360) and (361) of this book, with reference to five monks.
Once there were five monks in Sāvatthī. Each of them practised restraint of just one out of the five senses and each of them claimed that what he was practising was the most difficult. There were some heated arguments over this and they could not come to an agreement. Finally, they went to the Buddha to ask for his decision. The Buddha said to them, "Each of the senses is just as difficult to control as the other; but all monks must control all the five senses and not just one. Only those who control all the senses would escape from the round of rebirths."
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Guard the senses</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>362</Nr>
	  <Txt>He who is controlled in hand, in foot, in speech, and in the highest (i.e., the head); he who delights in meditation, and is composed; he who is alone, and is contented - him they call a monk.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>a Monk Who Killed a Swan (Hamsa)</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (362) of this book, with reference to a monk who killed a swan.
Once there was a monk who was very skilful in throwing stones; he could even hit fast-moving objects without fail. One day, while sitting with another monk after having their bath in the Aciravati River, he saw two swans flying at some distance. He told his friend that he would get one of the swans by throwing a stone at it. At that instant, the swan, hearing voices, turned its neck and the monk threw a pebble at the bird. The pebble went through one eye and came out of the other eye of the bird. The bird cried out in pain and agony and dropped dead at the feet of the young monk.
Other monks seeing the incident took the young monk to the Buddha. The Buddha reprimanded him and said, "My son, why have you killed this bird? Why especially you, a member of my Order, who should be practising loving-kindness to all beings and who should be striving ardently for liberation from the round of rebirths? Even during the period outside the Teaching, the wise practised morality and observed the precepts. A monk must have control over his hands, his feet and his tongue."
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>A monk is fully tamed</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>363</Nr>
	  <Txt>The monk who is controlled in tongue, who speaks wisely, who is not puffed up, who explains the meaning and the text - sweet, indeed, is his speech.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Monk Kokalika</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (363) of this book, with reference to Monk Kokalika.
Monk Kokalika had abused the two Chief Disciples, the Venerable Sariputta and the Venerable Maha Moggallana. For this evil deed Kokalika was swallowed up by the earth and had to suffer in Paduma Niraya. Learning about his fate, the monks remarked that Kokalika had to suffer grievously because he did not control his tongue. To those monks, the Buddha said, "Monks! A monk must have control over his tongue; his conduct must be good; his mind must be calm, subdued and not flitting about as it pleases."
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Control your tongue</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>364</Nr>
	  <Txt>That monk who dwells in the Dhamma, who delights in the Dhamma, who meditates on the Dhamma, who well remembers the Dhamma, does not fall away from the sublime Dhamma.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Thera Dhammarama</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (364) of this book, with reference to Thera Dhammarama.
When it was made known to the disciples that the Buddha would realize PariNibbāna in four months' time, most of the puthujjana monks (i.e., those who had not attained any of the Maggas) felt extremely depressed and were at a loss and did not know what to do. They just stayed close to the Buddha, hardly ever leaving his presence. However, there was a monk by the name of Dhammarama who kept to himself and did not go near the Buddha. His intention was to strive most ardently to attain arahatship before the passing away of the Buddha. So he strove hard in Insight Meditation Practice. Other monks, not understanding his attitude and his noble ambition, misunderstood his behaviour.
Those monks took Dhammarama to the Buddha and said to the Enlightened One, "Venerable Sir! This monk does not seem to have any affection or regard or reverence for you; he has been staying by himself while all the time other monks are staying close to Your Venerable presence." When other monks had said everything they wanted to say, Dhammarama respectfully explained to the Buddha why he had not come to see the Buddha and also reported that he had been striving his utmost in Insight Meditation Practice.
The Buddha was satisfied and was very pleased with the explanation and conduct of Dhammarama and he said, "My son, Dhammarama, you have done very well. A monk who loves and respects me should act like you. Those who made offerings of flowers, scents and incense to me are not really paying me homage. Only those who practise the Dhamma are the ones who truly pay homage to me."
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Deligthing in the dhamma</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>365</Nr>
	  <Txt>Let him not despise what he has received, nor should he live envying (the gains of) others. The monk who envies (the gains of) others does not attain tranquility. </Txt>
	</Par>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>366</Nr>
	  <Txt>Though receiving but little, if a monk does not despise his own gains, even the gods praise such a one who is pure in livelihood and is not slothful.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>A Monk Who Befriended a Follower of Devadatta</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verses (365) and (366) of this book, with reference to a monk who was on friendly terms with a follower of Devadatta.
Once, a monk disciple of the Buddha, being very friendly with a follower of Devadatta, paid a visit to the monastery of Devadatta and stayed there for a few days. Other monks reported to the Buddha that he had been mixing with the followers of Devadatta and that he had even gone to the monastery of Devadatta, spent there a few days, eating, sleeping and apparently enjoying the choice food and the comforts of that monastery. The Buddha sent for that monk and asked him whether what he had heard about his behaviour was true. The monk admitted that he had gone to the monastery of Devadatta for a few days, but he told the Buddha that he had not embraced the teaching of Devadatta.
The Buddha then reprimanded him and pointed out that his behaviour made him appear like a follower of Devadatta. To him the Buddha said, "My son, even though you have not embraced the doctrine of Devadatta, you are going about as if you were one of his followers. A monk should be contented with what he gets and should not covet other people's gains. A monk who is filled with envy at the good fortune of others will not attain collectedness (samadhi), or Insight, or the Path that leads to Nibbāna (Magga). Only the monk who is contented with whatever he gets will be able to attain collectedness, Insight and the Path."
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Be contented</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>367</Nr>
	  <Txt>He who has no thought of "l" and "mine" whatever towards mind and body, he who grieves not for that which he has not, he is, indeed, called a monk.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>The Giver of the First-Fruits of His Labour</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (367) of this book, with reference to a brahmin who was in the habit of making five offerings of first-fruits in charity. The first-fruits here refer to the first-fruits of the field. The first-fruits of the field are given in charity at the time of harvesting, at the time of threshing, at the time of storing, at the time of cooking and at the time of filling the plate.
One day, the Buddha saw the brahmin and his wife in his vision and knew that time was ripe for the couple to attain Anagami Fruition. Accordingly, the Buddha set out for their house and stood at the door for alms food. The brahmin who was then having his meal, facing the interior part of the house, did not see the Buddha. His wife who was near him saw the Buddha, but she was afraid that if her husband saw the Buddha standing at the door for alms-food, he would offer all his rice in the plate and, in that case, she would have to cook again. With this thought in her mind, she stood behind her husband so that he would not see the Buddha; when she quietly stepped backwards and slowly came to where the Buddha was standing, and whispered to him, "Venerable Sir! We do not have any alms-food for you today." But the Buddha had decided not to leave the house; he just shook his head. Seeing this gesture, the brahmin's wife could not control herself and she burst out laughing.
At that instant, the brahmin turned round and saw the Buddha. At once he knew what his wife had done, and he cried out, "O you, my wretched wife! You have ruined me." Then, taking up his plate of rice, he approached the Buddha and apologetically requested, "Venerable Sir! Please accept this rice which I have partly consumed." To him the Buddha replied, "O brahmin! Any rice is suitable for me, whether it is not yet consumed, or is partly consumed, or even if it is the last remaining spoonful." The brahmin was very much surprised by the Buddha's reply; at the same time, it made him happy because his offer of rice was accepted by the Buddha. The brahmin next asked the Buddha by what standard a monk was judged and how a monk was defined. The Buddha knew that both the brahmin and his wife had already learned something about mind and body (nama-rupa); so he answered, "O brahmin! One who is not attached to mind and body is called a monk."
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>A Monk has no attachment</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>368</Nr>
	  <Txt>The monk who abides in loving-kindness, who is pleased with the Buddha's Teaching, attains to that state of peace and happiness, the stilling of conditioned things.</Txt>
	</Par>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>369</Nr>
	  <Txt>Empty this boat, O monk! Emptied by you it will move swiftly. Cutting off lust and hatred, to Nibbāna you will thereby go.</Txt>
	</Par>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>370</Nr>
	  <Txt>Five cut off, five give up, five further cultivate. The monk who has gone beyond the five bonds is called a "Flood-Crosser".</Txt>
	</Par>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>371</Nr>
	  <Txt>Meditate, O monk! Be not heedless. Do not let your mind whirl on sensual pleasures. Do not be careless and swallow a ball of lead. As you burn cry not "This is sorrow".</Txt>
	</Par>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>372</Nr>
	  <Txt>There is no tranquility in one who lacks wisdom, nor is there wisdom in him who lacks tranquility. In whom are both tranquility and wisdom, he, indeed, is in the presence of Nibbāna.</Txt>
	</Par>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>373</Nr>
	  <Txt>The monk who has retired to a lonely abode, who has calmed his mind, who perceives the doctrine clearly, experiences a joy transcending that of men. </Txt>
	</Par>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>374</Nr>
	  <Txt>Whenever he reflects on the rise and fall of the Aggregates, he experiences joy and happiness. To "those who know" that (reflection) is Deathless.</Txt>
	</Par>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>375</Nr>
	  <Txt>And this becomes the beginning here for a wise monk: sense-control, contentment, restraint with regard to the Fundamental Code (Pātimokkha), association with beneficent and energetic friends whose livelihood is pure.</Txt>
	</Par>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>376</Nr>
	  <Txt>Let him be cordial in his ways and refined in conduct; filled thereby with joy, he will make an end of ill.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>a Great Many Monks</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verses (368) to (376) of this book, with reference to nine hundred monks.
Once there was a very rich lady in the town of Kuraraghara, about one hundred and twenty yojanas from Sāvatthī. She had a son who had become a monk; his name was Sona. On one occasion, Monk Sona passed through his home town. On his return from the Jetavana monastery his mother met him and organized a grand charity in his honour. Having heard that Monk Sona could expound the Dhamma very well she also requested him to expound the Dhamma to her and other people of the home town. Monk Sona complied with her request. So a pavilion was built and a meeting was organized for Monk Sona to give a discourse. There was a large gathering at the pavilion; the mother of the monk also went to listen to the Dhamma expounded by her son. She took all the members of her household with her leaving only a maid to look after the house.
While the lady was away, some thieves broke into the house. Their leader, however, went to the pavilion where the mistress of the house was, sat down near her and kept an eye on her. His intention was to get rid of her should she return home early on learning about the theft at her house. The maid seeing the thieves breaking into the house went to report the matter to her mistress, but the lady only said, "Let the thieves take all my money, I don't care; but do not come and disturb me while I am listening to the Dhamma. You'd better go back." So the maid went home.
There the girl saw the thieves breaking into the room where her mistress kept all her silverware. Again she went to the pavilion where her mistress was and reported to her that the thieves were taking away her silverware, but she was given the same answer as before. So she had to go back to the house. There she saw the thieves breaking into the room where her mistress kept her gold and she reported the matter to her mistress. This time, her mistress shouted at her, "O dear! Let the thieves take whatever they wish to take; why do you have to come and worry me again when I am listening to a discourse on the Dhamma? Why did you not go back when I told you to? Don't you dare come near me again and say things about the theft or the thieves."
The leader of the gang of thieves who was close at hand heard everything the lady had said and he was extremely surprised. Her words also kept him thinking, "If we take away the property of this wise and noble person, we will surely be punished; we might even be struck by lightning and our heads broken into many pieces." The leader got alarmed over this possibility and he hurried back to the house of the lady and made his followers return all the things they had taken. He then took all his followers to where the mistress of the house was; she was still at the pavilion, listening attentively to the Dhamma.
Thera Sona finished his exposition on the Dhamma with the crack of dawn and came down from the dais from where he had expounded the Dhamma. The leader of the thieves approached the rich, noble lady, paid respect to her and revealed his identity to her. He also related to her how they had plundered her house and also that they had returned all her property on hearing her words to her maid, who reported the theft to her during the night. Then, the leader and all the thieves asked the lady to forgive them for having wronged her. Then, they asked Thera Sona to admit them to the Order of monks. After the admission, each one of the nine hundred monks took a subject of meditation from Thera Sona and went to the nearby forest to practise meditation in seclusion.
From a distance of one hundred and twenty yojanas, the Buddha saw those monks and sent forth his radiance to them so that he seemed to be sitting in their midst.
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Radiating Loving-kindness leads to peace</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>377</Nr>
	  <Txt>As the jasmine creeper sheds its withered flowers, even so, O monks, should you totally cast off lust and hatred.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Five Hundred Monks</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (377) of this book, with reference to five hundred monks.
Five hundred monks from Sāvatthī, after taking a subject of meditation from the Buddha, set out for the forest to practise meditation. There, they noticed that the jasmine flowers which bloomed in the early morning dropped off from the plants onto the ground in the evening. Then the monks resolved that they would strive hard to free themselves from all moral defilements even before the flowers were shed from the plants. The Buddha, through his supernormal power, saw them from his Perfumed Chamber. He therefore sent forth his radiance to them and made them feel his presence. To them the Buddha said, "Monks! As the withered flower is shed from the plant, so also, should a monk strive to free himself from the round of rebirths."
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Cast off lust and hatred</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>378</Nr>
	  <Txt>The monk who is calm in body, calm in speech, calm in mind, who is well-composed, who has spewed out worldly things, is truly called a "peaceful one".</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Thera Santakaya</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (378) of this book, with reference to Thera Santakaya.
There was once a Thera named Santakaya, who had been a lion in his past existence. It is said that lions usually go out in search of food one day and then rest in a cave for the next seven days without moving. Thera Santakaya, having been a lion in his last existence, behaved very much like a lion. He moved about very little; his moments were slow and steady; and he was usually calm and composed. Other monks took his behaviour to be very queer and they reported about him to the Buddha. After hearing the account given by the monks, the Buddha said to all of them "Monks! A monk should be calm and composed; he should behave like Santakaya."
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Let go of all worldly things</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>379</Nr>
	  <Txt>By self do you censure yourself. By self do you examine yourself. Self-guarded and mindful, O monk, you will live happily.</Txt>
	</Par>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>380</Nr>
	  <Txt>Self, indeed, is the protector of self. Self, indeed, is one's refuge. Control, therefore, your own self as a merchant controls a noble steed.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Thera Nangalakula</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verses (379) and (380) of this book, with reference to Thera Nangala.
Nangala was a poor field labourer in the service of a farmer. One day, a monk, seeing him ploughing a field in his old clothes, asked him if he would like to become a monk. When he replied in the affirmative, the monk took him along to the monastery and made him a monk. After the admission to the Order, as instructed by his teacher, he left his plough and his old clothes in a tree not far away from the monastery. Because the poor man had left his plough to join the Order, he was known as Thera Nangala (nangala = plough). Due to better living conditions at the monastery, Thera Nangala became healthier and soon put on weight. However, after some time, he grew tired of the life of a monk and often felt like returning to home-life. Whenever this feeling arose in him, he would go to the tree near the monastery, the tree where he had left his plough and his old clothes. There he would reproach himself saying, "O you shameless man! Do you still want to put on these old rags and return to the hard, lowly life of a hired labourer ?" After this, his dissatisfaction with the life of a monk would disappear and he would go back to the monastery. Thus, he went to the tree at an interval of every three or four days, to remind himself of the wretchedness of his old life.
When other monks asked him about his frequent visits to the tree, he replied, "I have to go to my teacher." In course of time, he attained arahatship and he stopped going to the tree. Other monks, noticing this, asked him teasingly, "Why don't you go to your teacher now?" To those monks, he replied, "I used to go to my teacher because I had need of him; but now, I have no need to go to him." The monks understood what he meant by his answer and they went to the Buddha and reported, "Venerable Sir! Thera Nangala claims to have attained arahatship. It cannot be true; he must be boasting, he must be telling lies." To them the Buddha said, "Monks! Do not say so; for Nangala is not telling lies. My son Nangala, by reproaching himself and correcting himself, has indeed attained arahatship."
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>He who guards himself lives happily</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>381</Nr>
	  <Txt>Full of joy, full of confidence in the Buddha's Teaching, the monk will attain the Peaceful State, the stilling of conditioned things, the bliss (supreme).</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Thera Vakkali</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Veluvana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (381) of this book, with reference to Thera Vakkali.
Vakkali was a brahmin who lived in Sāvatthī. One day when he saw the Buddha going on an alms-round in the city, he was very much impressed by the noble appearance of the Buddha. At the same time, he felt much affection and great reverence for the Buddha and asked permission to join the Order just to be near him. As a monk, Vakkali always kept close to the Buddha; he did not care much about other duties of a monk and did not at all practise collectedness meditation. So, the Buddha said to him, "Vakkali, it will be of no use to you by always keeping close to me, looking at my face. You should practise collectedness meditation; for, indeed, only the one who sees the Dhamma sees me. One who does not see the Dhamma does not see me. So, you must leave my presence." When he heard those words Vakkali felt very depressed. He left the Buddha as ordered, and climbed the Gijjhakuta hill with the intention of committing suicide by jumping down from the peak.
The Buddha, knowing full well the extent of Vakkali's grief and despondency, reflected that because of his great sorrow and despondency Vakkali might miss the chance of attaining the Maggas. Accordingly, he sent forth his radiance to Vakkali, made him feel his presence and appeared as if in person to Vakkali. With the Buddha near him, Vakkali soon forgot all his sorrow; he became cheerful and very much heartened.
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>With joy and faith try to win your goal</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>382</Nr>
	  <Txt>The monk who, while still young, devotes himself to the Buddha's Teaching, illumines this world like the moon freed from a cloud.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Samanera Sumana</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Pubbarama monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (382) of this book, with reference to Samanera Sumana.
Samanera Sumana was a pupil of Thera Anuruddha. Although he was only seven years old he was an arahat, endowed with supernormal powers. Once, when his teacher Anuruddha was ill at a monastery in a forest of the Himalayas, he fetched water from the Anotatta lake which was five hundred yojanas away from the monastery. The journey was made not by land but by air through his supernormal power. Later, Thera Anuruddha took Samanera Sumana to the Buddha, who was then sojourning at Pubbarama, the monastery donated by Visakha.
There, other young monks and samaneras teased him by patting his head, or pulling his ears, nose and arms, and jokingly asked him if he was not feeling bored. The Buddha saw them and thought that he would make those young monks see the rare qualities of young Samanera Sumana. So it was made known by the Buddha that he wanted some samanera to get a jar of water from the Anotatta lake. The Venerable Ananda searched among the monks and samaneras of the Pubbarama monastery, but there was none who was able to undertake the job. Finally, the Venerable Ananda asked Samanera Sumana who readily agreed to fetch water from the Anotatta lake. He took a big golden jar front the monastery and soon brought the water from the Anotatta lake for the Buddha. As before, he went to the Anotatta lake and came back by air through his supernormal power.
At the congregation of the monks in the evening, the monks told the Buddha about the wonderful trip made by Samanera Sumana. To them the Buddha said, "Monks, one who practises the Dhamma vigilantly and zealously is capable of attaining supernormal powers, even though he is young."
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Even a young monk can be awake</Summary>
    </Verse>
  </Verses>
</Chapter>
