<Chapter xmlns:i="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.dhammasukha.org/dhammapada">
  <FirstParagraph>383</FirstParagraph>
  <LastParagraph>423</LastParagraph>
  <Nr>26</Nr>
  <Pali>Brāhmaṇa Vagga</Pali>
  <Title>The Brāhmaṇa</Title>
  <Verses>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>383</Nr>
          <Txt>Strive and cleave the stream. Discard, O brāhmaṇa, sense-desires. Knowing the destruction of conditioned things, be, O brāhmaṇa, a knower of the Unmade (Nibbāna).</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>a Brahmin Who Had Great Faith</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (383) of this book, with reference to a brahmin, who showed extreme devotion to some monks.
          Once, in Sāvatthī, there lived a brahmin who became extremely devoted to the Buddha and his Teaching, after hearing a discourse given by the Buddha. Every day, he invited the monks to his house for alms-food. When the monks arrived at his house, he addressed them as "arahats" and respectfully requested them to enter his house.
          When thus addressed, the puthujjana monks and the arahats felt embarrassed and they decided not to go to the brahmin's house the next day.
          When the brahmin found that the monks did not come to his house again he felt unhappy. He went to the Buddha and told him about the monks not coming to his house. The Buddha sent for those monks and asked for explanation. The monks told the Buddha about the brahmin addressing all of them as arahats.
          The Buddha then asked them whether they felt any false pride and undue elation when they were thus addressed. The monks answered in the negative. To them the Buddha said, "Monks, if you don't feel any false pride and undue elation when addressed as arahats, you are not guilty of breaking any of the rules of discipline of the monks. The fact is that the brahmin addressed you so because he was extremely devoted to the arahats. So. my sons, you should strive hard to get rid of craving and attain arahatship."
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Be a knower of the uncreated</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>384</Nr>
          <Txt>When in two states a brāhmaṇa goes to the Farther Shore, then all the fetters of that "one who knows" pass away.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Thirty Monks</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (384) of this book, with reference to thirty monks.
          On one occasion, thirty monks came to pay homage to the Buddha. The Venerable Sariputta, seeing that time was ripe and proper for those monks to attain arahatship, approached the Buddha and asked a question, solely for the benefit of those monks.
          The question was this: "What are the two dhammas?" To this the Buddha replied, "Sariputta! Tranquillity and Insight Meditation are the two dhammas."
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Cultivate collectedness and insight</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>385</Nr>
          <Txt>For whom there exists neither the hither nor the farther shore, nor both the hither and the farther shore, he who is undistressed and unbound, - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Mara</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (385) of this book, with reference to Mara.
          On one occasion, Mara came to the Buddha disguised as a man and asked him, "Venerable Sir, You often say the word 'param'. What is the meaning of that word?"
          The Buddha, knowing that it was Mara who was asking that question, chided him, "O wicked Mara! The words 'param' and 'aparam' have nothing to do with you. 'Param' which means 'the other shore' can be reached only by the arahats who are free from moral defilements."
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>The unbound person is a brāhmaṇa</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>386</Nr>
          <Txt>He who is meditative, stainless and secluded, he who has done his duty and is free from corruptions, he who has attained the Highest Goal - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>a Certain Brahmin</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (386) of this book, with reference to a brahmin.
          One day, a brahmin thought to himself, "Gotama Buddha calls his disciples 'brāhmaṇa'. I also am a brahmin by caste. Shouldn't I also be called a brāhmaṇa?" So thinking, he went to the Buddha and posed this question.
          To him the Buddha replied, "I do not call one a brāhmaṇa simply because of his caste; I only call him a brāhmaṇa, who has attained arahatship."
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>A brāhmaṇa is meditative and pure</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>387</Nr>
          <Txt>The sun shines by day; the moon is radiant by night. Armoured shines the warrior king. Meditating the brāhmaṇa shines. But all day and night the Buddha shines in glory.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Thera Ananda</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Pubbarama monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (387) of this book, with reference to the Venerable Ananda.
          It was the full moon day of the seventh month (Assayuja) when King Pasenadi of Kosala came to visit the Buddha. The king was then resplendent in his full royal regalia. 
          At that time, Thera Kaludayi was also present in the same room sitting at the edge of the congregation. He was in deep mental absorption (jhana), his body bright and golden. 
          In the sky, the Venerable Ananda noticed that the sun was setting and the moon was just coming out, both the sun and the moon radiating rays of light.
          The Venerable Ananda looked at the shining splendour of the king, of the thera, and of the sun and the moon. 
          Finally, the Venerable Ananda looked at the Buddha and he suddenly perceived that the light that was then radiating from the Buddha far surpassed the light shining from the others. Seeing the Buddha in his glory and splendour, the Venerable Ananda immediately approached the Buddha and burst forth, "O Venerable Sir! The light that shines forth from your noble body far surpasses the light from the king, the light from the thera, the light from the sun and the light from the moon."
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>The buddha shines day and night</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>388</Nr>
          <Txt>Because he has discarded evil, he is called a brāhmaṇa; because he lives in peace, he is called a samana; because he gives up the impurities, he is called a pabbajita - recluse.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>a Brahmin Recluse</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (388) of this book, with reference to a brahmin ascetic.
          Once there was a brahmin ascetic in Sāvatthī. One day, it occurred to him that the Buddha called his disciples pabbajita monks and since he also was a recluse, he should also be called a pabbajita.
          So he went to the Buddha and posed the question why he should not be called a pabbajita.
          The Buddha's answer to him was this: "Just because one is a recluse one does not automatically become a pabbajita; a pabbajita must have other qualifications also."
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>He is holy who has discarded all evil</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>389</Nr>
          <Txt>One should not strike a brāhmaṇa, nor should a brāhmaṇa vent (his wrath) on one who has struck him. Shame on him who strikes a brāhmaṇa! More shame on him who gives vent (to his wrath)!</Txt>
        </Par>
        <Par>
          <Nr>390</Nr>
          <Txt>Unto a brāhmaṇa that (non-retaliation) is of no small advantage. When the mind is weaned from things dear, whenever the intent to harm ceases, then and then only doth sorrow subside.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Thera Sariputta</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verses (389) and (390) of this book, with reference to the Venerable Sariputta.
          The Venerable Sariputta was often praised by many people for his patience and forbearance. His pupils usually said of him thus: "Our teacher is a man of great patience and extreme endurance. If he is abused or even beaten by others, he does not lose his temper but remains calm and composed."
          As this was often said of the Venerable Sariputta, a brahmin holding wrong views declared to the admirers of Sariputta that he would provoke the Venerable Sariputta into anger.
          At that moment, the Venerable Sariputta, who was on his alms-round, appeared on the scene; the brahmin went after him and hit him hard on his back with his hand. The thera did not even look round to see who was the person that attacked him, but proceeded on his way as if nothing had happened.
          Seeing the magnanimity and great fortitude of the noble thera, the brahmin was very much shaken. He got down on his knees at the feet of the Venerable Sariputta, admitted that he had wrongfully hit the thera, and asked for pardon. The brahmin then continued, "Venerable Sir, should you forgive me, kindly come to my house for alms-food."
          In the evening, other monks reported to the Buddha that the Venerable Sariputta had gone for alms-food to the house of a brahmin who had beaten him. Further, they observed that the brahmin was sure to get bolder and he would soon be assaulting other monks also.
          To those monks, the Buddha replied, "Monks, a true brāhmaṇa does not beat another true brāhmaṇa; only an ordinary man or an ordinary brahmin would beat an arahat in anger and ill will. This ill will should be eradicated by Anagami Magga."
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Do not harm an arahant</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>391</Nr>
          <Txt>He that does no evil through body, speech or mind, who is restrained in these three respects - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Theri Mahapajapati Gotami</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (391) of this book, with reference to Theri Mahapajapati Gotami.
          Mahapajapati Gotami was the stepmother of Gotama Buddha. On the death of Queen, seven days after the birth of Prince Siddhattha, Mahapajapati Gotami became the chief queen of King Suddhodana.
          At that time, her own son Nanda was only five days old. She let her own son be fed by a wet-nurse, and herself fed Prince Siddhattha, the future Buddha. Thus, Mahapajapati Gotami was a great benefactor to Prince Siddhattha.
          When Prince Siddhattha returned to Kapilavatthu after the attainment of Buddhahood, Mahapajapati Gotami went to see the Buddha and requested that women should also be allowed to enter the Buddhist Order as bhikkhunis; but the Buddha refused permission.
          Later, King Suddhodana died after attaining arahatship. Then, while the Buddha was sojourning at the Mahavana forest near Vesali, Mahapajapati, accompanied by five hundred ladies, came on foot from Kapilavatthu to Vasali. They had already shaven their heads and had put on the dyed robes.
          There, for a second time, Mahapajapati requested the Buddha to accept women in the Buddhist Order. The Venerable Ananda also interceded on her behalf. So, the Buddha complied, with the proviso that Mahapajapati abides by eight special conditions (garudhammas).
          Mahapajapati undertook to observe the garudhammas as required, and the Buddha admitted her into the Order. Thus, Mahapajapati was the first to be admitted to the Order of the Bhikkhunis.
          The other women were admitted to the Order after her by the monks as instructed by the Buddha.
          In course of time, it came to the minds of some bhikkhunis that Mahapajapati Gotami had not been properly admitted as a bhikkhuni because she did not have a preceptor; therefore, Mahapajapati Gotami was not a true bhikkhuni. With this thought in their mind, they stopped doing sabbath (uposatha) ceremonies and vassa (pavarana) ceremonies with her
          They went to the Buddha and posed the problem of Mahapajapati Gotami not having been properly admitted to the Order of bhikkhunis as she had no preceptor. To them the Buddha replied, "Why do you say so? I myself gave the eight garudhammas to Mahapajapati and she had learnt and practised the garudhammas as required by me. I myself am her preceptor and it is quite wrong for you to say that she has no preceptor. You should harbour no doubt whatsoever about an arahat."
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>A brāhmaṇa is well-restrained</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>392</Nr>
          <Txt>If from anybody one should understand the doctrine preached by the Fully Enlightened One, devoutly should one reverence him, as a brahmin reveres the sacrificial fire.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Thera Sariputta</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (392) of this book, with reference to the Venerable Sariputta.
          The Venerable Sariputta was born of brahmin parents of Upatissa village; that was why he was named Upatissa. His mother was Sari. His very close friend was Kolita, another brahmin youth, son of Moggali. Both the youths were searching for the right doctrine, which would lead them to liberation from the round of rebirths, and both of them had a great desire to enter a religious Order. First, they went to Sancaya, but they were not satisfied with his teaching. Then they wandered all over Jambudipa looking for a teacher who would show them the way to the Deathless, but their search was fruitless. After some time, they parted company but with the understanding that the one who found the true dhamma first should inform the other.
          About that time, the Buddha arrived at Rajagaha with a company of monks, including Thera Assaji, one of the group of the first Five Monks (Pancavaggis). While Thera Assaji was on an alms-round, Upatissa saw the thera and was very much impressed by his noble countenance. So Upatissa respectfully approached the thera and asked who his teacher was, what doctrine his teacher taught, and also briefly to explain the doctrine to him. Thera Assaji then told Upatissa about the arising of the Buddha and about his sojourn at the Veluvana monastery in Rajagaha. The thera also quoted a short stanza connected with the Four Noble Truths.
          The verse runs thus:
          Ye dhamma hetuppa bhava tesam hetum tathagato aha tesanca yo nirodho evam vadi maha samano.
          It means:
          The Tathagata has declared the cause and also the cessation of all phenomena which arise from a cause. This is the doctrine held by the Great Samana.
          When the verse was only half-way through, Upatissa attained Sotapatti Fruition.
          As promised, Upatissa went to his friend Kolita to inform him that he had found the true dhamma. Then the two friends, accompanied by two hundred and fifty followers, went to the Buddha who was then at Rajagaha. When they arrived at the Veluvana monastery, they asked permission to enter the Buddhist Order, and both Upatissa and Kolita, together with their two hundred and fifty followers, were admitted as monks.  Upatissa, son of Sari, and Kolita, son of Moggali, then came to be known as Sariputta and Moggallana.
          Soon after their admission to the Order, the Buddha expounded to them a dhamma and the two hundred and fifty monks attained arahatship; but Moggallana and Sariputta attained arahatship only at the end of seven days and fifteen days respectively. The reason for the delay in their attainment of arahatship was that they had made a wish for Chief Discipleship, which required much more striving to achieve perfection.
          The Venerable Sariputta always remembered that he had been able to meet the Buddha and attain the Deathless through the Venerable Assaji. So, he always paid obeisance in the direction where his teacher was and he always went to bed with his head lying in the same direction.
          Other monks who were staying with him at the Jetavana monastery misinterpreted his actions and said to the Buddha, "Venerable Sir! The Venerable Sariputta still worships the various directions, viz., the East, the South, the West, the North, the Nadir and the Zenith, as he has done before as a brahmin youth; it seems as if he has not yet given up his old beliefs."
          The Buddha sent for the Venerable Sariputta and Sariputta explained to the Buddha that he was only paying obeisance to his teacher, the Venerable Assaji, and that he was not worshipping the various directions. The Buddha was satisfied with the explanation given by the Venerable Sariputta and said to the other monks,"Monks! The Venerable Sariputta was not worshipping the various directions; he was only paying obeisance to his teacher and benefactor, through whom he had attained the Deathless. It is quite right and proper for him to pay homage to such a teacher."
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Honour to whom honour is due</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>393</Nr>
          <Txt>Not by matted hair, nor by family, nor by birth does one become a brāhmaṇa. But in whom there exist both truth and righteousness, pure is he, a brāhmaṇa is he.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Jatila, the Brahmin</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (393) of this book, with reference to Jatila, a brahmin ascetic who wore matted hair.
          Once, a brahmin ascetic thought to himself that the Buddha called his disciples 'brāhmaṇas' and that he being a brahmin by birth should also be called a 'brāhmaṇa'.
          Thinking thus, he went to see the Buddha and put forward his view. But the Buddha rejected his view and said, "O brahmin, I do not call one a brāhmaṇa because he keeps his hair matted or simply because of his birth; I call one a brāhmaṇa only if he fully comprehends the Four Noble Truths."
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Pure is he who is truthful and righteous</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>394</Nr>
          <Txt>What is the use of your matted hair, O witless man? What is the use of your antelope skin garment? Within, you are full of passions; without, you embellish yourself. </Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>a Deceitful Brahmin</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Kutagara monastery in Vesali, the Buddha uttered Verse (394) of this book, with reference to a deceitful brahmin.
          Once, a deceitful brahmin climbed up a tree near the city-gate of Vesali and kept himself hanging upside down like a bat from one of the branches of the tree. From this very awkward position, he kept on muttering, "O people! Bring me a hundred heads of cattle, many pieces of silver and a number of slaves. If you do not bring these to me, and if I were to fall down from this tree and die, this city of yours will surely come to ruin."
          The people of the town, fearing that their city night be destroyed if the brahmin were to fall down and die, brought all the things he demanded and pleaded with him to come down.
          The monks hearing about this incident reported to the Buddha and the Buddha replied that the deceitful one could only cheat the ignorant people but not the wise ones.
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Be pure within</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>395</Nr>
          <Txt>The person who wears dust-heap robes, who is lean, whose veins stand out, who meditates alone in the forest - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Kisagotami</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Gijjhakuta hill, the Buddha uttered Verse (395) of this book, with reference to Kisagotami.
          On one occasion, Sakka, king of the devas, came with his followers to pay homage to the Buddha. At the same lime, Theri Kisagotami, by her supernormal power came through the sky to pay homage to the Buddha. But when she saw Sakka and his entourage paying homage to the Buddha, she retreated.
          Sakka seeing her, asked the Buddha who the lady was, and the Buddha replied, "O Sakka! She is my daughter Kisagotami. Once, she came to me in sorrow and distress through the loss of her son and I made her see the impermanent, the unsatisfactory and the non-self nature of all conditioned things. As a consequence of that she attained Sotapatti Fruition, joined the Order, and became an arahat. She is one of my eminent female disciples and is matchless in the ascetic practice of wearing robes made from rags collected from a dust heap."
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>A brāhmaṇa meditates alone in the forest</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>396</Nr>
          <Txt>I do not call him a brāhmaṇa merely because he is born of a (brahmin) womb or sprung from a (brahmin) mother. He is merely a "Dear-addresser", if he be with impediments. He who is free from impediments, free from clinging - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>a Brahmin</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (396) of this book, with reference to a brahmin.
          Once, a brahmin from Sāvatthī thought that since the Buddha called his disciples 'brāhmaṇas', he should also be called a 'brāhmaṇa' because he was born of brahmin parents. When he told the Buddha about this, the Buddha replied to him, "O brahmin! I do not call him a brāhmaṇa just because he is born of brahmin parents. I call him a brāhmaṇa only if he is free from moral defilements and cut off all clinging to existence."
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Be non-possessive and non-attached</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>397</Nr>
          <Txt>He who has cut off all fetters, who trembles not, who has gone beyond ties, who is unbound - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Uggasena, the Son of a Rich Man*</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (397) of this book, with reference to Uggasena, son of a rich man.
          After marrying a dancer from a theatrical troupe, Uggasena was trained by his father-in-law who was an acrobat, and became very skilful in acrobatics. One day while he was demonstrating his skill, the Buddha came on the scene. After hearing the Buddha's teaching, Uggasena attained arahatship while he was still performing his feats on top of a long bamboo pole. After that, he climbed down from the pole and pleaded with the Buddha to accept him as a monk and was accordingly admitted into the Order.
          One day, when other monks asked him whether he did not have any feeling of fear while climbing down from such a great height (i.e., about ninety feet), he answered in the negative. The monks took that to mean that Uggasena was claiming to have attained arahatship even then. So, they went to the Buddha and said, "Venerable Sir! Uggasena claims himself to be an arahat; he must be telling lies." To them the Buddha replied, "Monks, one who has cut off all fetters, like my son Uggasena, has no fear."
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>A brāhmaṇa has destroyed all fetters</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>398</Nr>
          <Txt>He who has cut the strap (hatred), the thong (craving), and the rope (heresies), together with the appendages (latent tendencies), who has thrown up the cross-bar (ignorance), who is enlightened (Buddha) - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Two Brahmins</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (398) of this book, with reference to two brahmins.
          Once there lived in Sāvatthī two brahmins, each of whom owned a bullock. Each claimed that his bullock was better and stronger. At last, they agreed to put their animals to a test. So they went to the bank of the Aciravati River and there they filled up a cart with sand. One after the other, the bullocks pulled the cart, but they only pulled in vain, because the cart, did not move and only the ropes broke off. The monks seeing this reported to the Buddha and the Buddha said to them, "Monks! It is easy to break off the straps which you can see with your eyes; anyone can break them or cut them. But my sons, a monk should cut the strap of ill will and the thong of craving which are within you and which bind you."
          Verse 398: Him I call a brāhmaṇa, who has cut the strap (of ill will), the thong (of craving) and the cord (of wrong views together with latent defilements), who has lifted the bar that fastens the door (of ignorance), and who knows the Truth.
          At the end of the discourse five hundred monks attained arahatship.
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>A brāhmaṇa has no hatred</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>399</Nr>
          <Txt>He who, without anger, endures reproach, flogging and punishments, whose power and potent army is patience - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>the Abusive Brahmin Brothers</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Veluvana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (399) of this book, with reference to the abusive Bharadvaja brothers.
          Once there was a brahmin, whose wife was in the habit of blurting out a string of words whenever she sneezed or when something or someone touched her unawares. One day, the brahmin invited some of his friends to a meal and suddenly she blurted out some words. Since she was a Sotapanna, the words "Namo tassa bhagavato arahato sammsambhuddassa" automatically came out of her mouth. These words of veneration to the Buddha were very much disliked by her husband, the brahmin. So, in anger, he went to the Buddha hoping to put some challenging questions to the Buddha. His first question was, "What do we have to kill to be able to live happily and peacefully?" and his second question was, "Killing of what dhamma do you approve of?" To these questions, the Buddha replied," O brahmin, to be able to live happily and peacefully, one will have to kill ill will (dosa). Killing one's ill will is liked and praised by the Buddhas and the arahats." After hearing the Buddha, the brahmin was so impressed and satisfied with the answer that he asked to be permitted to enter the Order. Accordingly, he entered the Order and later became an arahat.
          This brahmin had a brother who was very notorious for his abusive words and was known as Akkosaka Bharadvaja, the abusive Bharadvaja. When Akkosaka Bharadvaja heard that his brother had joined the Order of the monks, he was furious. He went straight away to the monastery and abused the Buddha. The Buddha in his turn asked, "O brahmin, let us suppose you offered some food to some guests and they left the house without taking the food. Since the guests did not accept your food, to whom would that food belong?" To this question the brahmin answered that the food would be his. On receiving that answer, the Buddha said, "In the same way, O brahmin, since I do not accept your abuse, the abuse would only go back to you." Akkosaka Bharadvaja instantly realized the sagacity of those words and he felt a great respect for the Buddha. He also entered the Order and in due course became an arahat.
          After Akkosaka Bharadvaja had entered the Order, his two younger brothers also came to see the Buddha with the same intention of abusing the Buddha. They too were made to see the light by the Buddha and they also, in their turn, entered the Order. Eventually, both of them became arahats.
          One evening, at the congregation of the monks, the monks said to the Buddha, "O how wonderful and how great are the virtues of the Buddha! The four brahmin brothers came here to abuse the Buddha; instead of arguing with them, he made them see the light, and as a result, the Buddha has become a refuge to them." To them, the Buddha replied, "Monks! Because I am patient and forbearing, and do no wrong to those who do me wrong, I have become a refuge to many."
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>A brāhmaṇa is patient</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>400</Nr>
          <Txt>He who is not wrathful, but is dutiful, virtuous, free from craving, self-controlled and bears his final body, - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Thera Sariputta</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Veluvana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (400) of this book, with reference to the Venerable Sariputta.
          While the Buddha was in residence at the Veluvana monastery, the Venerable Sariputta, accompanied by five hundred monks, entered Nalaka Village and stood at the door of the house of his own mother for alms-food. His mother invited them into the house. But while she was offering food to her son she said, "O you consumer of left-overs, you who have abandoned eighty crores to become a monk, you have ruined us." Then, she offered alms-food to the other monks and said to them rudely, "You all have used my son as your attendant; now eat your food." The Venerable Sariputta said nothing in reply but he just meekly took his bowl and came back to the monastery. Back at the monastery, the monks told the Buddha how the Venerable Sariputta had patiently borne the scolding and abuses of his mother. To them, the Buddha said that arahats never get angry, they never lose their temper.
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>A brāhmaṇa is not wrathful</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>401</Nr>
          <Txt>Like water on a lotus leaf, like a mustard seed on the point of a needle, he who clings not to sensual pleasures - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Theri Uppalavanna*</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (401) of this book, with reference to Theri Uppalavanna.
          Once, some monks were talking about the arahat Theri Uppalavanna being molested by the young Nanda who was then swallowed up by the earth. In this connection, they asked the Buddha whether arahats do not enjoy sensual pleasures as they have the same physical make-up like any other people. To them the Buddha replied, "Monks! Arahats do not enjoy sensual pleasures; they do not indulge in sensual pleasures, for they do not cling to objects of sense and to sensual pleasures, just as water does not cling to the lotus leaf or the mustard seed to the tip of an awl."
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>A brāhmaṇa lets go of sensual pleasures</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>402</Nr>
          <Txt>He who realizes here in this world the destruction of his sorrow, who has laid the burden aside and is emancipated, - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>a Certain Brahmin</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (402) of this book, with reference to a certain brahmin, whose slave became an arahat.
          Once, there was a young slave of a brahmin. One day, fleeing from the house of his master he joined the Order of the monks, and in due course, he attained arahatship. On one occasion, while he went on an alms-round with the Buddha, his former master, the brahmin, saw him and grabbed him firmly by the robe. When the Buddha asked what the matter was, the brahmin explained that the young monk was his slave at one time. To him the Buddha said, "This monk has laid down the burden (of the khandhas)." The brahmin took that to mean that his slave had become an arahat. So to make sure, he asked the Buddha whether it was true that the young monk had become an arahat, and the Buddha confirmed his statement.
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>A brāhmaṇa has laid the burden aside</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>403</Nr>
          <Txt>He whose knowledge is deep, who is wise, who is skilled in the right and wrong way, who has reached the highest goal - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Theri Khema*</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Gijjhakuta hill, the Buddha uttered Verse (403) of this book, with reference to Theri Khema.
          One night, Sakka, king of the devas, came with his followers to pay homage to the Buddha. While they were with the Buddha, Theri Khema, by her supernormal power, also came through the sky to pay homage to the Buddha. But because Sakka and his company were there with the Buddha, she just paid obeisance to the Buddha, and soon left him. Sakka asked the Buddha who that bhikkhuni was and the Buddha replied, "She is one of my pre-eminent disciples; she is known as Theri Khema. She is matchless amongst the bhikkhunis in wisdom and she knows how to differentiate the right way from the wrong way."
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>A brāhmaṇa has reached his ultimate goal</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>404</Nr>
          <Txt>He who is not intimate either with householders or with the homeless ones, who wanders without an abode, who is without desires - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Thera Tissa</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (404) of this book with reference to Thera Tissa.
          Thera Tissa, after taking a subject of meditation from the Buddha, went to a mountain side. There, he found a cave which suited him and he decided to spend the three months of the rainy season (vassa) in that cave. So he stayed in the cave and went to the village for alms-food every morning. In the village, there was a certain elderly woman who regularly offered him alms-food. In the cave, there also lived the guardian spirit of the cave. As the thera was one whose practice of morality was pure, the cave-spirit dared not live in the same cave with the noble thera; at the same time, he did not have the courage to ask the thera to leave the place. So he thought of a plan that would enable him to find fault with the thera and thus cause him to leave the cave.
          The cave-spirit possessed the son of the elderly woman from the house where the thera usually went for his alms-food. He caused the boy to behave in a very peculiar way, turning his head backwards, and rolling his wide open eyes. His mother got alarmed and was in tears. The cave-spirit, who possessed the boy, then said "Let your teacher, the thera, wash his feet with water and pour that water on the head of your son." The next day when the thera came to her house for alms-food, she did as she was advised by the cave-spirit and the boy was left in peace. The cave-spirit went back to the cave and waited at the entrance for the return of the thera. When the thera returned from his alms-round, the cave-spirit revealed himself and said, "I am the spirit guarding this cave. O you physician, do not enter this cave." The thera knew that he had lived a clean life from the day he had become a thera, so he replied that he did not remember practising medicine. Then the cave-spirit accused him that in that very morning he had cured a young boy possessed by an ogre at the house of the elderly woman. But the thera reflected that it was not, in fact, practising medicine and he realized that even the cave spirit could find no other fault with him. That gave him a delightful satisfaction (piti) with himself, and abandoning piti and concentrating hard on Insight Meditation he attained arahatship then and there, while still standing at the entrance to the cave.
          As the thera had now become an arahat, he advised the cave-spirit to leave the cave. The thera continued to stay there till the end of the vassa, and then he returned to the Buddha. When he told the other monks about his encounter with the cave-spirit, they asked him whether he did not get angry with the cave-spirit when he was forbidden to enter the cave. The thera answered in the negative but they did not believe him. So they went to the Buddha and said, "Thera Tissa claims himself to be an arahat ; he is not speaking the truth." To them the Buddha replied,"Monks, my son Tissa was speaking the truth when he said he did not get angry. He has indeed become an arahat he is no longer attached to anyone; he has no occasion to get angry with anyone nor any need to associate with others."
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>A brāhmaṇa has no intimacy with any</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>405</Nr>
          <Txt>He who has laid aside the cudgel in his dealings with beings, whether feeble or strong, who neither harms nor kills - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>a Certain Monk</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (405) of this book, with reference to a certain monk.
          Once, a monk after taking a subject of meditation from the Buddha went to a forest to practise meditation. After he had attained arahatship he came back to the Buddha to offer his deep and profound gratitude to the Buddha. On his way, he passed through a village. Just as he was going through the village, a woman having quarreled with her husband came out of her house and followed the monk. The husband coming after his wife, seeing her behind the monk, thought that the monk was taking his wife away. So he shouted at the monk and threatened to beat him. His wife entreated him not to beat the monk, but that made him more furious. As a result, the thera was beaten black and blue by the husband. After beating the monk to his heart's content, he took away his wife along with him and the monk continued on his way.
          On arrival at the Jetavana monastery, other monks saw the bruises over the whole body of the monk and they attended to his bruises. When they asked him if he did not get angry with the man who had beaten him so sorely, he answered in the negative. So the other monks went to the Buddha and reported that the monk had falsely claimed to have attained arahatship. To them the Buddha replied, "Monks! Arahats have laid aside the stick and the sword. They do not get angry even if they are beaten." Thus, the Buddha confirmed that the monk had, indeed, become an arahat.
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>A brāhmaṇa is absolutely harmless</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>406</Nr>
          <Txt>He who is friendly amongst the hostile, who is peaceful amongst the violent, who is unattached amongst the attached, - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Four Samaneras</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (406) of this book, with reference to four samaneras who were arahats.
          Once, the wife of a brahmin sent her husband the brahmin to the Jetavana monastery to invite four monks to an alms-meal at their house. She told him to specifically request for senior monks who were also true brāhmaṇas. But four seven year old arahat samaneras, viz., Samkicca, Pandita, Sopaka and Revata were sent along with him. When his wife saw the young samaneras she was very much dissatisfied and blamed the brahmin for bringing such young samaneras who were even younger than her grandson. She was, in fact, furious with her husband, and so she sent him back to the monastery to get older monks. In the meantime she refused to give the young samaneras the higher seats reserved for the monks; they were given lower seats and she did not offer them alms-food.
          When the brahmin arrived at the monastery, he met the Venerable Sariputta and invited him to his house. When the Venerable Sariputta arrived at the house of the brahmin, he saw the four young arahat samaneras and asked them if they had been offered alms-food yet. On learning that the arahat samaneras had not been given alms-food yet and also that food had been prepared only for four persons the Venerable Sariputta returned to the monastery without accepting alms-food from the house of the brahmin. So his wife sent the brahmin back again to the monastery to get another senior monk. This time, the Venerable Maha Moggallana came along with the brahmin, but he also returned to the monastery without accepting alms-food when he learned that the young samaneras had not been offered alms-food and also that food had been prepared only for four persons.
          By this time, the samaneras were feeling hungry. Sakka, king of the devas, seeing the state of things took the form of an old brahmin and came to the house. The brahmin and his wife paid respect to the old brahmin and offered him a seat of honour, but Sakka just sat on the ground and paid respect to the four samaneras. Then he revealed that he was Sakka. Seeing that Sakka himself was paying respect to the young samaneras, the brahmin couple offered alms-food to all the five. After the meal, Sakka and the samaneras manifested their supernormal power by going right up into the sky through the roof. Sakka went back to his celestial abode, the samaneras returned to the monastery.
          When other monks asked the samaneras whether they did net get angry when the brahmin couple refused to offer alms-food to them, they answered in the negative. The monks not believing them reported to the Buddha that the four young samaneras were falsely claiming to be arahats. To them the Buddha said, "Monks, arahats bear no ill will towards those who are hostile to them."
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>A brāhmaṇa is friendly</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>407</Nr>
          <Txt>In whom lust, hatred, pride, detraction are fallen off like a mustard seed from the point of a needle - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Thera Mahapanthaka</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Veluvana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (407) of this book, with reference to Thera Mahapanthaka, elder brother of Culapanthaka*.
          Thera Mahapanthaka was already an arahat when his younger brother Culapanthaka joined the Order. Culapanthaka was born a dullard because he had made fun of a very dull monk in one of his past existences. Culapanthaka could not even memorize one verse in four months' time. Mahapanthaka was disappointed with his younger brother and asked him to leave the monastery as he was not worthy of the Order.
          It was in this connection that, on one occasion, the monks asked the Buddha why Mahapanthaka, even though he was an arahat, turned his younger brother Culapanthaka out of the monastery. They also added "Do the arahats still lose their temper? Do they still have moral defilements like ill will in them?" To them the Buddha replied,"Monks! Arahats have no moral defilements like passion and ill will in them. My son Mahapanthaka acted as he did with a view to benefiting his brother and not out of ill will."
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>A brāhmaṇa has discarded all passions</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>408</Nr>
          <Txt>He who utters gentle, instructive, true words, who by his speech gives offence to none - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Thera Pilindavaccha</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Veluvana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (408) of this book, with reference to Thera Vaccha, who was also known as Thera Pilindavaccha, due to his offensive ways.
          Thera Pilindavaceha had a very offensive way of addressing people: he would often say, "Come here, you wretch", or "Go there, you wretch" and such other things. Other monks reported about him to the Buddha. The Buddha sent for him, and spoke to him on the matter. Then, on reflection the Buddha found that for the past five hundred existences, the thera had been born only in the families of the brahmins, who regarded themselves as being superior to other people. So the Buddha said to the monks, "Monks! Thera Vaccha addresses others as 'wretch' only by force of habit acquired in the course of his five hundred existences as a brahmin, and not out of malice. He has no intention of hurting others, for an arahat does not harm others."
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>A brāhmaṇa gives offence to none</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>409</Nr>
          <Txt>He who in this world takes nothing that is not given, be it long or short, small or great, fair or foul - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>a Certain Thera</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (409) of this book, with reference to a certain thera.
          One day, a brahmin from Sāvatthī put his upper garment outside his house to air it. A thera found that garment as he was going back to the monastery. Thinking that it was a piece of cloth thrown away by someone and therefore ownerless, the thera picked it up. The brahmin looking out of his window saw the thera picking up the piece of clothing and came after the thera, abusing and accusing him. "You shaven head! You are stealing my clothing", he said; the thera promptly returned the piece of clothing to the brahmin.
          Back at the monastery, the thera related the above Incident to other monks, and they made fun of him and jokingly asked him whether the cloth was long or short, coarse or fine. To this question the thera answered, "Whether the clothing is long or short, coarse or fine matters not to me; I am not at all attached to it." Other monks then reported to the Buddha that the thera was falsely claiming himself to be an arahat. To them the Buddha replied, "Monks! The thera speaks the truth; an arahat does not take anything that is not given him."
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>A brāhmaṇa steals not</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>410</Nr>
          <Txt>He who has no longings, pertaining to this world or to the next, who is desireless and emancipated - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Thera Sariputta</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (410) of this book, with reference to Thera Sariputta.
          On one occasion, Thera Sariputta accompanied by five hundred monks went to a monastery near a small village to spend the vassa. At the end of the vassa, Thera Sariputta wanted robes for young monks and samaneras. So he said to the monks, "If people come to offer robes, send them to me or inform me"; and then he left for the Jetavana monastery to pay homage to the Buddha. Other monks misunderstood Thera Sariputta's instructions, and said to the Buddha, "Venerable Sir! Thera Sariputta is still attached to material things like robes and other requisites of a monk." To them the Buddha replied, "Monks! My son Sariputta has no more craving in him. He told you to bring the robes to him, so that the chances to perform meritorious deeds may not decrease for lay-disciples, and the chances to accept whatever they may properly receive may not be reduced for young monks and samaneras."
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>A brāhmaṇa is desireless</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>411</Nr>
          <Txt>He who has no longings, who, through knowledge, is free from doubts, who has gained a firm footing in the Deathless (Nibbāna) - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Thera Maha Moggallana</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (411) of this book, with reference to Thera Maha Moggallana.
          On one occasion, the monks told the Buddha about Thera Maha Moggallana the same thing they had said of Thera Sariputta that he still had attachment to worldly things. To them the Buddha said that Thera Maha Moggallana had discarded all craving.
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>A brāhmaṇa has no longings</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>412</Nr>
          <Txt>Herein he who has transcended both good and bad and the ties as well, who is sorrowless, stainless, and pure - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Samanera Revata</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Pubbarama monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (412) of this book, with reference to Samanera Revata.
          One day, the monks said to the Buddha, "Revata is getting many offerings from people, he is gaining fame and fortune. Even though he lives alone in the forest, through supernormal power he has now built five hundred pinnacled monasteries for five hundred monks." To them the Buddha said, "Monks, my son Revata has discarded all craving; he has transcended both good and evil."
          Verse 412: Him I call a brāhmaṇa, who, in this world, has transcended both ties good and evil; who is sorrowless and, being free from the taints of moral defilements, is pure.
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>A brāhmaṇa has transcended good and evil</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>413</Nr>
          <Txt>He who is spotless as the moon, who is pure, serene, and unperturbed, who has destroyed craving for becoming - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Thera Candabha</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (413) of this book, with reference to Thera Candabha.
          Candabha had, in a previous existence, made offerings of sandalwood to a stupa where the relics of Kassapa Buddha were enshrined. For this good deed, he was reborn in a brahmin family in Sāvatthī. He was born with a distinguishing mark, viz., a circle of light radiating from around his navel. As this circle of light resembled the moon he came to be known as Candabha. Some brahmins, taking advantage of this unusual feature, put him on a cart and took him round the town for exhibition and only those who paid a hundred or a thousand were allowed to touch him. On one occasion, they stopped at a place between the town and the Jetavana monastery. To ariyas going to the Jetavana monastery, they said, 'What is the use of your going to the Buddha and listening to his discourses? There is no one who is as powerful as Candabha. One who touches him will get rich; why don't you come and see ?" The ariyas then said to them, "Only our teacher is powerful; he is unrivalled and matchless."
          Then the brahmins took Candabha to the Jetavana monastery to compete with the Buddha. But when Candabha was in the presence of the Buddha, the ring of light went out by itself. When Candabha was taken out of sight of the Buddha, the ring of light returned automatically; it again disappeared when taken back to the presence of the Buddha. Candabha then asked the Buddha to give him the mantra (words of incantation) that would make the ring of light disappear from around his navel. The Buddha told him that the mantra could be given only to a member of his Order. Candabha told the brahmins that he was getting a mantra from the Buddha and that after mastering the mantra he would be the greatest person in the whole of Jambudipa. So the brahmins waited outside the monastery.
          Meanwhile, Candabha became a monk. He was instructed to contemplate the body, i.e., to reflect on the repulsiveness and impurity of the thirty-two constituents of the body. Within a few days, Candabha attained arahatship. When the brahmins who were waiting outside the monastery came to enquire whether he had acquired the mantra, Candabha replied. "You people had better go back now; as for me I am no longer in a position to go along with you." Other monks, hearing him, went to the Buddha and said, "Candabha is falsely claiming that he has become an arahat." To them the Buddha replied, "Candabha speaks the truth; he has eradicated all moral intoxicants."
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>A brāhmaṇa is pure</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>414</Nr>
          <Txt>He who has passed beyond this quagmire, this difficult path, the ocean of life (samsāra), and delusion, who has crossed and gone beyond, who is meditative, free from craving and doubts, who, clinging to naught, has attained Nibbāna - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Thera Sivali</Title>
        <Txt>While residing in the Kundadhana forest near the city of Kundakoliya, the Buddha uttered Verse (414) of this book, with reference to Thera Sivali.
          Princess Suppavasa of Kundakoliya was in pregnancy for seven years and then for seven days she was in labour pains. She kept contemplating the unique qualities of the Buddha, the Dhamma and the Samgha and in the end she sent her husband to the Buddha to pay obeisance to him on her behalf and to inform him of her condition. When informed of the condition of the princess, the Buddha said, "May Suppavasa be free from danger and from sorrow; may she give birth to a healthy noble son in safety." As these words were being spoken, Suppavasa gave birth to her son at her house. On that very day, soon after the birth of the child, the Buddha and some monks were invited to the house. Alms-food was offered there and the newly born child offered filtered water to the Buddha and the monks. To celebrate the birth of the child, the parents invited the Buddha and the monks to their house to offer food for seven days.
          When the child grew up he was admitted to the Order and as a monk he was known as Sivali. He attained arahatship as soon as his head was shaved off. Later, he became famous as the monk who received the largest amount of offerings. As a recipient of offerings he was unsurpassed.
          On one occasion, the monks asked the Buddha why Sivali, with the qualifications to become an arahat, was confined in his mother's womb for seven years. To them the Buddha replied,"Monks! In a previous existence, Sivali was the son of a king who lost his kingdom to another king. In trying to regain their kingdom he had besieged the city on the advice of his mother. As a result, the people in the city were without food or water for seven days. It was for this evil deed that Sivali was imprisoned in his mother's womb for seven years. But now, Sivali has come to the end of all dukkha; he has realized Nibbāna."
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>A brāhmaṇa clings to naught</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>415</Nr>
          <Txt>He who in this world giving up sense-desires, would renounce worldly life and become a homeless one, he who has destroyed sense-desires and becoming - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Thera Sundarasamudda</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (415) of this book, with reference to Thera Sundarasamudda.
          Sundarasamudda was the son of a rich man from Sāvatthī. After he had entered the Order, he left for Rajagaha, which was forty-five yojanas away from Sāvatthī, to practise meditation. One day, while some festivities were going on in Sāvatthī, the parents of Sundarasamudda missed him very much; they also felt sorry for their son who was missing all the enjoyment and they wept. As they were weeping, a courtesan came to them and asked what the matter was. On hearing about their son, the courtesan said, "If I could make your son leave the Order and return to the life of a lay man how would you reward me?" The parents answered that they would make her rich. The courtesan then asked for a large sum of money and left for Rajagaha with a number of followers.
          At Rajagaha, she rented a house with seven-tiered pinnacles on the route where Thera Sundarasamudda would come on his alms-round. She prepared good food and waited for him. On the first few days, she offered alms-food to the thera at the door of her house. Later, she invited him to come inside. Meanwhile, she paid money to some children to come and play just outside the house about the time the thera usually came on his alms-round. This gave her the excuse that it was very dusty and noisy on the ground floor; with this excuse she invited the thera to the top floor to have his alms-food. The thera consented and went up and as soon as he had entered the room, the courtesan closed the door. Then she started seducing the thera. She said to the thera, "Venerable Sir! Please be my youthful and energetic husband, and I will be your dearly beloved wife. After our long and happy wedded life we can both leave it to enter the Order and strive our very best to attain Nibbāna." When he heard these words the thera suddenly realized his mistake and got alarmed. Then he said to himself, "Indeed, by being negligent and unmindful I have made a great mistake."
          At that instant, the Buddha saw from his Perfumed Chamber what was happening to Thera Sundarasamudda at Rajagaha. He called the Venerable Ananda and said to him, "Ananda! On an upper storey of a pinnacled building in Rajagaha, there now goes on a struggle between Sundarasamudda and a courtesan; but in the end the thera will be the winner." After saying this to Ananda, the Buddha sent forth his radiance to the thera, made him feel his presence, and said, "My son! Be resolute and get rid of love of wealth and sensual pleasures."
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>A brāhmaṇa has given up sense-desires</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>416</Nr>
          <Txt>He who in this world giving up craving, would renounce worldly life and become a homeless one, he who has destroyed craving and becoming - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Thera Jatila</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Veluvana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (416*) of this book, with reference to Thera Jatila.
          Soon after the passing away (PariNibbāna) of Kassapa Buddha, an arahat thera went round for donations to build a gold stupa where the relics of Kassapa Buddha were to be enshrined. The thera came to the house of a goldsmith while he and his wife were engaged in a heated quarrel. The goldsmith shouted at the thera and said, "You had better thrown your stupa into the water and go away." His wife then said to the goldsmith, "If you are angry with me you should abuse me only; you can even beat me if you like; but why do you have to abuse the Buddha and the thera? Surely, you have done a grievous wrong!" Hearing her words, the goldsmith realized the enormity of the wrong he had done and wanted to make atonement for it. So, he made some gold flowers, put them into three gold pots and offered them to be put into the relic chamber of the stupa of Kassapa Buddha.
          In his present existence he was conceived in the womb of a rich man's daughter who had had an illicit love affair. When the child was born, she put it into a pot and floated it down the stream. A young woman who was bathing in the stream saw the child in the pot and took it with her. She adopted him and named him Jatila. Later, on the advice of a thera the woman sent Jatila to Taxila where he had his education. While at Taxila the thera arranged for him to stay at the house of a merchant who was a disciple of his. In due course, Jatila married the daughter of the merchant. Soon after the marriage, a large mound of gold appeared in the backyard of the house which was newly built for the couple. Three sons were born out of this marriage. After that, Jatila joined the Order and attained arahatship within a few days.
          On one occasion, as the Buddha went on an alms-round with five hundred monks including Jatila, they came to the house of the sons of Jatila. His sons offered alms-food to the Buddha and his disciples for fifteen days. Some time afterwards, the monks asked Jatila whether he was still attached to his mound of gold and his sons, and he answered that he had no more attachment to them. The monks then said to the Buddha that Jatila was falsely claiming to have attained arahatship. To them the Buddha said, "Monks! Jatila has got rid of craving and pride; he has indeed attained arahatship."
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>A brāhmaṇa has given up craving</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>417</Nr>
          <Txt>He who, discarding human ties and transcending celestial ties, is completely delivered from all ties - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Thera Nataputtaka</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (417) of this book, with reference to Thera Nataputtaka, who was the son of a dancer.
          Once, the son of a dancer was going round the streets singing and dancing when he had a chance to listen to a discourse given by the Buddha. After listening to the discourse, he entered the Order and attained arahatship soon afterwards. One day, while the Buddha and the monks including Nataputtaka were going on an alms-round, they came across the son of another dancer dancing in the street. Seeing the young man dancing, the other monks asked Nataputtaka whether he still liked dancing. And Nataputtaka answered, "No, I do not." The monks then went to the Buddha and told him that Thera Nataputtaka was falsely claiming to have attained arahatship. Thereby, the Buddha said, "Monks! Nataputtaka has gone beyond all bonds of attachment; he has become an arahat."
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>A brāhmaṇa has discarded all bonds</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>418</Nr>
          <Txt>He who has given up likes and dislikes, who is cooled and is without defilements, who has conquered the world and is strenuous - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Thera Nataputtaka</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Veluvana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (418) of this book, with reference to another Thera Nataputtaka, son of another dancer.
          As in the previous story, the son of a dancer had entered the Order and had attained arahatship. Other monks went to the Buddha and told him about Thera Nataputtaka claiming to have attained arahatship. To them the Buddha said, "Monks! Nataputtaka has given up taking delight in all things."
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Give up likes and dislikes</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>419</Nr>
          <Txt>He who in every way knows the death and rebirth of beings, who is non-attached, well-gone, and enlightened, - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</Txt>
        </Par>
        <Par>
          <Nr>420</Nr>
          <Txt>He whose destiny neither gods nor gandhabbas nor men know, who has destroyed all corruptions, and is far removed from passions (Arahant) - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Thera Vangisa</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verses (419) and (420) of this book, with reference to Thera Vangisa.
          Once, in Rajagaha, there was a brahmin by the name of Vangisa who by simply tapping on the skull of a dead person could tell whether that person was reborn in the world of the devas, or of the human beings, or in one of the four lower worlds (apayas). The brahmins took Vangisa to many villages and people flocked to him and paid him ten, twenty or a hundred to find out from him where their various dead relatives were reborn.
          On one occasion, Vangisa and his party came to a place not far from the Jetavana monastery. Seeing those people who were going to the Buddha, the brahmins invited them to come to Vangisa who could tell where their relatives had been reborn. But the Buddha's disciples said to them, "Our teacher is one without a rival, he only is the Enlightened One." The brahmins took that statement as a challenge and took Vangisa along with them to the Jetavana monastery to compete with the Buddha. The Buddha, knowing their intention, instructed the monks to bring the skulls of a person reborn in niraya, of a person reborn in the animal world, of a person reborn in the human world, of a person reborn in the deva world and also of an arahat. The five were then placed in a row. When Vangisa was shown those skulls he could tell where the owners of the first four skulls were reborn but when he came to the skull of the arahat he was at a loss. Then the Buddha said,"Vangisa, don't you know? I do know where the owner of that skull is." Vangisa then asked the Buddha to let him have the magical incantation (mantra) by which he could thus know; but the Buddha told him that the mantra could be given only to a monk. Vangisa then told the brahmins to wait outside the monastery while he was being taught the mantra. Thus, Vangisa became a monk and as a monk, he was instructed by the Buddha to contemplate the thirty-two constituents of the body. Vangisa diligently practised meditation as instructed by the Buddha and attained arahatship within a short time.
          When the brahmins who were waiting outside the monastery came to ask Vangisa whether he had acquired the mantra, Vangisa said, "You all had better go now; as for me, I should no longer go along with you." Other monks hearing him thought he was telling lies, so they went to the Buddha and said, "Venerable Sir! Vangisa is falsely claiming to have attained arahatship." To them the Buddha said,"Monks! Vangisa really knows the death and rebirth of beings."
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>A brāhmaṇa is not attached</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>421</Nr>
          <Txt>He who has no clinging to Aggregates that are past, future, or present, who is without clinging and grasping - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Theri Dhammadinna</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Veluvana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (421) of this book, with reference to Theri Dhammadinna.
          Once, there was a lay-disciple of the Buddha named Visakha in Rajagaha. After hearing the Buddha's discourses again and again Visakha attained Anagami Fruition and he said to his wife, "Please accept all my property; from today, I'm not going to take part in any of the affairs of the house." His wife Dhammadinna retorted, "Who would swallow the spittle you have thrown up?" Then she asked permission from him to enter the Order and became a bhikkhuni. After becoming a bhikkhuni she went to a monastery in a small village in the company of other bhikkhunis to practise meditation. Within a short time, she attained arahatship and returned to Rajagaha.
          Visakha, hearing that Dhammadinna had returned, went to see her and asked her some questions. When he asked her about the first three maggas she answered him; but when he asked her questions on the arahatta magga and phala she said, "O lay-disciple! This matter is out of your depth; if you want, you may go and ask the Buddha." When Visakha asked the Buddha, the Buddha said, "Dhammadinna has already answered your question. If you ask me I shall have to give the same answer." Saying this the Buddha confirmed the fact that Dhammadinna had attained arahatship.
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>A brāhmaṇa yearns for naught</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>422</Nr>
          <Txt>The fearless, the noble, the hero, the great sage, the conqueror, the desireless, the cleanser (of defilements), the enlightened, - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Angulimala</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (422) of this book, with reference to Thera Angulimala.
          On one occasion, King Pasenadi and Queen Mallika made an alms-offering to the Buddha and his monks numbering five hundred in all, on a scale which could not be surpassed by anyone else. At that ceremony, each monk was to have an elephant holding a white umbrella over his head as a sunshade. However, they could get only four hundred and ninety-nine trained elephants and so they had to put in an untrained elephant and it was allotted to hold the umbrella over Thera Angulimala. Every one was afraid that the untrained elephant might give trouble, but when brought near Thera Angulimala it was quite docile.
          It was with reference to this incident that the monks later asked Angulimala whether he did not get frightened or not. To this question Angulimala answered that he was not frightened. The monks then went to the Buddha and said that Thera Angulimala claimed to have attained arahatship. To them the Buddha said, "Monks! It is quite true that Angulimala was not afraid; those who are like him are also not afraid."
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>A brāhmaṇa is enlightened</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
        <Par>
          <Nr>423</Nr>
          <Txt>That sage who knows his former abodes, who sees the blissful and the woeful states, who has reached the end of births, who, with superior wisdom, has perfected himself, who has completed (the holy life), and reached the end of all passions - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</Txt>
        </Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
        <Title>Devahita the Brahmin</Title>
        <Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (423) of this book, with reference to Devahita, a brahmin.
          On one occasion, the Buddha suffered from a gastric ailment and he sent Thera Upavana to get some hot water from Devahita the brahmin. The brahmin was very pleased to have this rare opportunity to offer something to the Buddha. So, in addition to hot water he also gave the thera some molasses for the Buddha. At the monastery Thera Upavana gave a warm bath to the Buddha; after the bath he offered the Buddha a mixture of molasses and hot water. After drinking the mixture there was instant relief. The brahmin then came and asked the Buddha, "Venerable Sir! An offering made to whom gives one the greatest benefit?" To him the Buddha said, "Brahmin! An offering made to one who has given up all evil is the most beneficial."
        </Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>A brāhmaṇa has perfected himself</Summary>
    </Verse>
  </Verses>
</Chapter>
