<Chapter xmlns:i="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.dhammasukha.org/dhammapada">
  <FirstParagraph>90</FirstParagraph>
  <LastParagraph>99</LastParagraph>
  <Nr>7</Nr>
  <Pali>Arahanta Vagga</Pali>
  <Title>The Worthy</Title>
  <Verses>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>90</Nr>
	  <Txt>For him who has completed the journey, for him who is sorrowless, for him who from everything is wholly free, for him who has destroyed all Ties, the fever (of passion) exists not. </Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>the Question Asked by Jivaka</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the mango-grove monastery of Jivaka, the Buddha uttered Verse (90) of this book, with reference to the question raised by Jivaka to the Buddha.
Devadatta, on one occasion, tried to kill the Buddha by pushing a big rock from the peak of Gijjhakuta mountain (Vulture's Peak). The rock struck a ledge on the side of the mountain and a splinter struck the big toe of the Buddha. The Buddha was taken to the mango-grove monastery of Jivaka. There, Jivaka, the renowned physician, attended on the Buddha; he put some medicine on the toe of the Buddha and bandaged it. Jivaka then left to see another patient in town, but promised to return and remove the bandage in the evening. When Jivaka returned that night, the city-gates were already closed and he could not come to see the Buddha that night. He was very upset because if the bandage was not removed in time, the whole body would become very hot and the Buddha would be very ill.
Just about this time, the Buddha asked Thera Ananda to remove the bandage from his big toe and found that the wound was completely healed. Jivaka came to the monastery early next morning and asked the Buddha whether he felt great pain and distress the previous night. The Buddha replied, "Jivaka! Ever since I attained Buddhahood there has been no pain and distress for me."
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>No suffering for the emancipated</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>91</Nr>
	  <Txt>The mindful exert themselves. To no abode are they attached. Like swans that quit their pools, home after home they abandon (and go). </Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Thera Mahakassapa</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Veluvana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (91) of this book, with reference to Thera Mahakassapa.
The Buddha once spent the vassa at Rajagaha with a number of monks. About two weeks before the end of the vassa, the Buddha informed the monks that they would soon be leaving Rajagaha and told them to prepare for departure. Some monks stitched and dyed new robes, some washed the old robes. When some monks saw Mahakassapa washing his robes, they speculated, "There are so many people inside and outside Rajagaha who love and respect Thera Mahakassapa and are constantly looking to all his needs; is it possible that the Thera would leave his lay devotees here and follow the Buddha elsewhere?"
At the end of fifteen days, on the eve of his departure, the Buddha thought that there might be some occasions like alms-food offering ceremonies, initiation of novices, funerals, etc., and so it would not be proper for all the monks to leave. So he decided that some monks should remain at the Veluvana monastery and that the most suitable person would be Thera Mahakassapa. Consequently, Thera Mahakassapa remained in Rajagaha with some junior monks.
Then the other monks said scornfully, "Mahakassapa has not accompanied the Buddha, just as we have predicted!" The Buddha heard their remark and said to them, "Monks! Do you wish to say that my son Kassapa is attached to his lay disciples of Rajagaha and to the things they offer him? You are very much mistaken. My son Kassapa remains here under my instruction; he is not attached to anything here."
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Arahants are free from attachment</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>92</Nr>
	  <Txt>They for whom there is no accumulation, who reflect well over their food, who have Deliverance which is Void and Signless, as their object - their course, like that of birds in the air, cannot be traced.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Thera Belatthasisa</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (92) of this book, with reference to Thera Belatthasisa.
Thera Belatthasisa, after going on an alms-round in the village, stopped on the way and took his food there. After the meal, he continued his round of alms for more food. When he had collected enough food he returned to the monastery, dried up the rice and hoarded it. Thus, there was no need for him to go on an alms-round every day; he then remained in jhana collectedness for two or three days. Arising from jhana collectedness he ate the dried rice he had stored up, after soaking it in water. Other Bhikkhunis thought ill of the thera on this account, and reported to the Buddha about his hoarding of rice. Since then, the hoarding of food by the monks has been prohibited.
As for Thera Belatthasisa, since he stored up rice before the ruling on hoarding was made and because he did it not out of greed for food, but only to save time for meditation practice, the Buddha declared that the thera was quite innocent and that he was not to be blamed.
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Be not attached to food</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>93</Nr>
	  <Txt>He whose corruptions are destroyed, he who is not attached to food, he who has Deliverance, which is Void and Signless, as his object - his path, like that of birds in the air, cannot be traced.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Thera Anuruddha</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (93) of this book, with reference to Thera Anuruddha.
Thera Anuruddha was one day looking for some discarded pieces of cloth in a rubbish heap to make into a robe as his old robe was getting soiled and torn. Jalini, his wife of a previous existence, who was now in a deva world, saw him. Knowing that he was looking for some cloth, she took three pieces of good deva material and put them in the rubbish heap, making them barely visible. The thera found the pieces of cloth and took them to the monastery. While he was making the robe, the Buddha arrived with his Chief Disciples and senior disciples and they also helped stitch the robe.
Meanwhile, Jalini, assuming the form of a young lady, came to the village and learnt about the arrival of the Buddha and his disciples and also how they were helping Thera Anuruddha. She urged the villagers to send good delicious food to the monastery and consequently there was more than enough for all. Other monks, seeing so much surplus, put the blame on the thera and said, "Thera Anuruddha should have asked his relatives and lay disciples to send just enough food; may be, he just wanted to show off that he had so many devotees." To those monks, the Buddha said, "Monks, do not think my son Anuruddha has asked his relatives and lay disciples to send rice gruel and other foods. My son the thera did not ask for anything; arahats do not talk about such things like food and clothing. The excessive amount of food brought to the monastery this morning was due to the promptings of a celestial being and not of a man."
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Free are the undefiled ones</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>94</Nr>
	  <Txt>He whose senses are subdued, like steeds well-trained by a charioteer, he whose pride is destroyed and is free from the corruptions - such a steadfast one even the gods hold dear.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Thera Mahakaccayana</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Pubbarama monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (94) of this book, with reference to Thera Mahakaccayana.
On a full moon day, which was also the end of the vassa, Sakka with a large company of devas came to pay homage to the Buddha, who was then in residence at Pubbarama, the monastery built by Visakha. At that time, the Buddha was being attended upon by the Chief Disciples and all the senior monks. Thera Mahakaccayana, who spent the vassa in Avanti, had not yet arrived, and a seat was kept vacant for him. Sakka paid homage to the Buddha with flowers, incense and perfumes. On seeing a vacant seat he declared how he wished that Thera Mahakaccayana would come so that he could pay obeisance to him also. At that instant Mahakaccayana arrived; Sakka was very pleased and eagerly paid obeisance to him with flowers, incense and perfumes.
The monks were awed by Sakka paying obeisance to Mahakaccayana, but some monks thought that Sakka was being partial to Mahakaccayana. To them, the Buddha said, "One who is restrained in his senses is loved by both men and devas."
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>The sense-controlled are dear to all</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>95</Nr>
	  <Txt>Like the earth a balanced and well-disciplined person resents not. He is comparable to an Indakhila. Like a pool unsullied by mud, is he; to such a balanced one life's wanderings do not arise. </Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Thera Sariputta</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (95) of this book, with reference to the Chief Disciple Sariputta and a young monk.
It was the end of the vassa; and Thera Sariputta was about to set out on a journey with some followers. A young monk, who bore some grudge against the thera, approached the Buddha and falsely reported that Thera Sariputta had abused him and beaten him. The Buddha therefore sent for the thera and questioned him, and Thera Sariputta replied as follows: "Venerable Sir! How could a monk, who steadfastly keeps his mind on the body, set out on a journey without apologizing, after doing wrong to a fellow monk? I am like the earth, which feels no pleasure when flowers are cast on it, nor resentment when rubbish and excreta are piled upon it. I am also like the door-mat, the beggar, the bull with broken horns; I also feel abhorrence for the impurity of the body and am no longer attached to it."
When Thera Sariputta spoke thus, the young monk felt very much distressed and wept bitterly, and admitted that he had lied about the Chief Disciple Sariputta. Then the Buddha advised Thera Sariputta to accept the apology of the young monk, lest a heavy punishment should fall on him and get his head crushed. The young monk then admitted that he had done wrong and respectfully asked for pardon. Thera Sariputta pardoned the young monk and also asked to be forgiven if he also had done any wrong.
All those present talked in praise of Thera Sariputta, and the Buddha said, "Monks, a monk like Sariputta has no anger or ill will in him. Like the earth and the door-post, he is patient, tolerant, and firm; like the lake free from mud, he is serene and pure."
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Like the earth arahants resent not</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>96</Nr>
	  <Txt>Calm is his mind, calm is his speech, calm is his action, who, rightly knowing, is wholly freed, perfectly peaceful, and equipoised.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>a Samanera from Kosambi</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (96) of this book, with reference to a samanera, a pupil of Thera Tissa from Kosambi.
Once, a seven year old boy was made a samanera at the request of his father. Before his head was shaved the boy was given a subject of meditation. While he was being shaved, the boy had his mind fixed steadfastly on the object of meditation; as a result, he attained arahatship as soon as they finished shaving his head.
After some time, Thera Tissa, accompanied by the samanera, set out for Sāvatthī to pay homage to the Buddha. On the way, they spent one night in a village monastery. The thera fell asleep, but the young samanera sat up the whole night beside the bed of the old thera. Early in the morning, the old thera thought it was time to wake up the young samanera. So he roused up the samanera with a palm-leaf fan, and accidentally hit the eye of the samanera with the handle of the fan and damaged the eye. The samanera covered that eye with one hand and went about doing his duties of getting water for the thera to wash his face and clean his mouth, sweeping the floor of the monastery, etc. When the young samanera offered water with one hand to the thera, the thera chided him, and said that he should offer things with both hands. Only then, did the thera learn how the samanera lost his eye. At that instant, he realized that he had wronged a truly noble person. Feeling very sorry and humiliated, he made an apology to the samanera. But the samanera said that it was not the fault of the thera, nor his own fault, but that it was only the result of kamma, and so the thera was not to feel sad about it. But the thera could not get over the unfortunate incident.
Then they continued their journey to Sāvatthī and arrived at the Jetavana monastery where the Buddha was in residence. The thera then told the Buddha that the young samanera who came along with him was the most noble person he had ever met, and related all that had happened on their way. The Buddha listened to him, and replied, "My son, an arahat does not get angry with anyone he is restrained in his senses and is perfectly calm and serene."
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Calm are the peaceful</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>97</Nr>
	  <Txt>The man who is not credulous, who understands the Uncreate (Nibbāna), who has cut off the links, who has put an end to occasion (of good and evil), who has eschewed all desires, he indeed, is a supreme man.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Thera Sariputta</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (97) of this book, with reference to Thera Sariputtta.
Thirty monks from a village had arrived at the Jetavana monastery to pay homage to the Buddha. The Buddha knew that the time was ripe for those monks to attain arahatship. So, he sent for Sariputta, and in the presence of those monks, he asked, "My son Sariputta, do you accept the fact that by meditating on the senses one could realize Nibbāna ?" Sariputta answered, "Venerable Sir, in the matter of the realization of Nibbāna by meditating on the senses, it is not that I accept it because I have faith in you; it is only those who have not personally realized it, that accept the fact from others." Sariputta's answer was not properly understood by the monks; they thought, "Sariputta has not given up wrong views yet; even now, he has no faith in the Buddha."
Then the Buddha explained to them the true meaning of Sariputta's answer."Monks, Sariputta's answer is simply this; he accepts the fact that Nibbāna is realized by means of meditation on the senses, but his acceptance is due to his own personal realization and not merely because I have said it or somebody else has said it. Sariputta has faith in me; he also has faith in the consequences of good and bad deeds."
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Noble is he who is not credulous</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>98</Nr>
	  <Txt>Whether in village or in forest in vale or on hill, wherever Arahants dwell - delightful, indeed, is that spot.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Thera Revata</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (98) of this book, with reference to Thera Revata of the Acacia (khadira) Forest.
Revata was the youngest brother of the Chief Disciple, Sariputta. He was the only one of the brothers and sisters of Sariputta who had not left home for the homeless life. His parents were very anxious to get him married. Revata was only seven years old when his parents arranged a marriage for him to a young girl. At the wedding reception, he met an old lady who was one hundred and twenty years old, and he realized that all beings are subject to ageing and decay. So, he ran away from the house and went straight to a monastery, where there were thirty monks. Those monks had been requested earlier by Thera Sariputta to make his brother a samanera if he should come to them. Accordingly, he was made a samanera and Thera Sariputta was informed about it.
Samanera Revata took a subject of meditation from those monks and left for an acacia forest, thirty yojanas away from the monastery. At the end of the vassa, the samanera attained arahatship. Thera Sariputta then asked permission from the Buddha to visit his brother, but the Buddha replied that he himself would go there. So the Buddha accompanied by Thera Sariputta, Thera Sivali and five hundred other monks set out to visit Samanera Revata.
The journey was long, the road was rough and the area was uninhabited by people; but the devas looked to all the needs of the Buddha and the monks on the way. At an interval of every yojana, a monastery and food were provided, and they travelled at the rate of a yojana a day. Revata, learning about the visit of the Buddha, also made arrangements to welcome him. By supernormal power he created a special monastery for the Buddha and five hundred monasteries for the other monks, and made them comfortable throughout their stay there.
On their return journey, they travelled at the same rate as before, and came to the Pubbarama monastery on the eastern end of Sāvatthī at the end of the month. From there, they went to the house of Visakha, who offered them alms-food. After the meal, Visakha asked the Buddha if the place of Revata in the acacia forest was pleasant.
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>It is good to be amongst the awakened</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>99</Nr>
	  <Txt>Delightful are the forests where worldlings delight not; the passionless will rejoice (therein), (for) they seek no sensual pleasures.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>a Woman</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (99) of this book, with reference to a woman of doubtful character.
A monk, after taking a subject of meditation from the Buddha, was practising meditation in an old garden. A woman of doubtful character came into the garden and, seeing the monk, tried to attract his attention and seduce him. The thera got frightened; at the same time, his whole body was diffused with some kind of delightful satisfaction. The Buddha saw him from his monastery, and with his supernormal power, sent rays of light to him, and the monk received this message, which said, "My son, where worldlings seek sensual pleasures is not the place for monks; monks should take delight in forests where worldlings find no pleasure."
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Forests are delightful to the awakened</Summary>
    </Verse>
  </Verses>
</Chapter>
