<Chapter xmlns:i="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.dhammasukha.org/dhammapada">
  <FirstParagraph>100</FirstParagraph>
  <LastParagraph>115</LastParagraph>
  <Nr>8</Nr>
  <Pali>Sahassa Vagga</Pali>
  <Title>Thousands</Title>
  <Verses>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>100</Nr>
	  <Txt>Better than a thousand utterances, comprising useless words, is one single beneficial word, by hearing which one is pacified.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Tambadathika</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (100) of this book, with reference to Tambadathika, the executioner of thieves.
Tambadathika served the king as an executioner of thieves for fifty-five years; he had just retired from that post. One day, after preparing rice gruel at his house, he went to the river for a bath; he had intended to take the specially prepared rice gruel on his return. As he was about to take the rice gruel, Thera Sariputta, who had just arisen from sustained absorption in collectedness (jhana samapatti), stood at his door for alms-food. Seeing the thera, Tambadathika thought to himself, "Throughout my life, I have been executing thieves; now I should offer this food to the thera." So, he invited Thera Sariputta to come in and respectfully offered the rice gruel.
After the meal, the thera taught him the Dhamma, but Tambadathika could not pay attention, because he was so agitated as he recollected his past life as an executioner. When the thera knew this, he decided to ask Tambadathika tactfully whether he killed the thieves because he wished to kill them or because he was ordered to do so. Tambadathika answered that he was ordered to kill them by the king and that he had no wish to kill. Then the thera asked, "If that is so, would you be guilty or not ?" Tambadathika then concluded that, as he was not responsible for the evil deeds, he was not guilty. He, therefore, calmed down, and requested the thera to continue his exposition. As he listened to the Dhamma with proper attention, he came very close to attaining Sotapatti Magga, and reached as far as anuloma nana.* After the discourse, Tambadathika accompanied Thera Sariputta for some distance and then returned home. On his way home a cow (actually a demon in the guise of a cow) gored him to death.
When the Buddha came to the congregation of the monks in the evening, they informed him about the death of Tambadathika. When asked where Tambadathika was reborn, the Buddha told them that although Tambadathika had committed evil deeds throughout his life, because he comprehended the Dhamma after hearing it from Thera Sariputta and had already attained anuloma nana before he died, he was reborn in the Tusita deva world. The monks wondered how such an evil-doer could have such great benefit after listening to the Dhamma just once. To them the Buddha said that the length of a discourse is of no consequence, for one single word of sense can produce much benefit.
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>A single useful sentence</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>101</Nr>
	  <Txt>Better than a thousand verses, comprising useless words, is one beneficial single line, by hearing which one is pacified.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Bahiyadaruciriya</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (101) of this book, with reference to Bahiyadaruciriya.
A group of merchants went out to sea in a boat; their boat was wrecked at sea and all, except one, died. The only survivor got hold of a plank and eventually came to land at the port of Supparaka. As he was naked, he tied the plank to his body, got hold of a bowl, and sat in a place where people could see him. Passers-by gave him rice and gruel; some took him for an arahat and talked in praise of him. Some brought clothes for him to wear but he refused, fearing that by wearing clothes, people would give less to him. Besides, because some said that he was an arahat, he mistakenly came to think that he really was one. Thus, because he was a man of wrong views who was wearing a piece of wood as his clothing, he came to be known as Bahiyadaruciriya.
At about this time, Mahabrahma, who had been his friend in one of his previous existences, saw him going astray and felt that it was his duty to put Bahiya on the right path. So, Mahabrahma came to him in the night and said to him "Bahiya, you are not an arahat yet, and what is more, you do not have the qualities that make one an arahat." Bahiya looked up at Mahabrahma and said, "Yes, I must admit that I am not an arahat, as you have said. I now realize that I have done a great wrong. But is there anyone else in this world now who is an arahat?" Mahabrahma then told him that there lived in Sāvatthī Gotama Buddha, an arahat, who was perfectly self-enlightened.
Bahiya, realizing the enormity of his guilt, felt very much distressed and ran all the way to Sāvatthī. Mahabrahma helped him by his supernormal power, so that the whole stretch of one hundred and twenty yojanas was covered in one night. Bahiya found the Buddha going on an alms-round with other monks and respectfully followed him. He pleaded with the Buddha to teach him the Dhamma, but the Buddha replied that since they were on an alms-round it was not yet time for a religious discourse. And again, Bahiya pleaded, "Venerable Sir, one cannot know the danger to your life or to my life, so please talk to me about the Dhamma." The Buddha knew that Bahiya had made the journey of one hundred and twenty yojanas in one night, and also that he was overwhelmed with joy at seeing the Buddha. That was why the Buddha did not want to talk about the Dhamma immediately but wanted him to calm down to enable him to take in the Dhamma properly. Still, Bahiya persistently pleaded. So, while standing on the road, the Buddha said to Bahiya, "Bahiya, when you see an object, be conscious of just the visible object; when you hear a sound, be conscious of just the sound; when you smell or taste or touch something, be conscious of just the smell, the taste or the touch; and when you think of anything, be conscious of just the mind-object."
After hearing the above discourse, Bahiya attained arahatship and he asked permission from the Buddha to join the Order. The Buddha told him to get the robes, the bowl and other requisites of a monk. On his way to get them, he was gored to death by a cow which was, in fact, an ogress in the likeness of a cow. When the Buddha and the other monks came out after having had their meal, they found Bahiya lying dead on a rubbish heap. As instructed by the Buddha, the monks cremated the body of Bahiya and had his bones enshrined in a stupa.
Back at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha told the monks that Bahiya had realized Nibbāna. He also told them that as far as speed was concerned in attaining Magga Insight (abhinna), Bahiya was the fastest, the best (Etadaggam). The monks were puzzled by the statement made by the Buddha and they asked him why and when Bahiya became an arahat. To this, the Buddha replied, "Bahiya attained arahatship while he listened to my instructions given to him on the road when we were on the alms-round." The monks wondered how one could attain arahatship after listening to just a few sentences of the Dhamma. So, the Buddha told them that the number of words or the length of a speech did not matter if it was beneficial to someone.
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>A single useful verse</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>102</Nr>
	  <Txt>Should one recite a hundred verses, comprising useless words, better is one single word of the Dhamma, by hearing which one is pacified.</Txt>
	</Par>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>103</Nr>
	  <Txt>Though one should conquer a million men in battlefield, yet he, indeed, is the noblest victor who has conquered himself.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Theri Kundalakesi</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verses (102) and (103) of this book, with reference to Theri Kundalakesi.
Kundalakesi was the daughter of a rich man from Rajagaha. She had led a very secluded life; but one day, she happened to see a thief being led out to be killed and she immediately fell in love with him. Her parents had to pay for the freedom of the thief, and they married her off to him. Although she loved her husband very dearly, her husband being a thief, was only attracted to her property and her jewels. One day, he coaxed her to put on all her jewellery and led her to a mountain saying that he wanted to make some offerings to the guardian spirit of the mountain because that guardian spirit had saved his life when he was about to be killed. Kundalakesi went along with her husband, but when they reached their destination, the thief revealed that he intended to kill her and take her jewels. She pleaded with him to take her jewels, but to spare her life, but it was of no avail. She then realized that if she did not get rid of her husband, there would be no way of escape for her. She felt she must be cautious and crafty. So she said to her husband that as they would be together only for a few moments more, she wanted to pay respect to him for the last time. So saying, and going round the man respectfully, she pushed him off the crag, taking him unaware.
After this, she had no desire to return home. She left all her jewellery hanging on a tree, and went on her way, without any idea where she was going. She happened to come to a place of some Paribbajikas (female wandering ascetics) and she herself became a Paribbajikas. The Paribbajikas taught her all their one thousand problems in sophistry; being intelligent she mastered all of them within a short time. Then her teachers told her to go out into the world and if she should find somebody who could answer all her questions, to become a pupil to him. Kundalakesi went throughout the length and breadth of Jambudipa, openly challenging everyone else to compete with her. Accordingly, she came to be known as "Jambukaparibbajika."
On one occasion, she came to Sāvatthī. Before entering the city for alms-food she made a mound of sand and stuck a branch of eugenia on it, her usual sign of invitation to all others to take up her challenge. Thera Sariputta took up her challenge. Kundalakesi asked him a thousand questions and Thera Sariputta answered them all. When his turn came, he asked her just this, "What is the one? (ekam nama kim)." Kundalakesi could not answer, so she asked Thera Sariputta to teach her the answer to the question. Thera Sariputta replied that she should first become abhikkhuni; so she became a bhikkhuni, by the name of Theri Kundalakesi. Within a few days, she became an arahat.
Soon after this, the monks asked the Buddha, "Could it be possible for Bhikkhuni Kundalakesi to become an arahat after listening to the Dhamma only a little?" They also added that this lady had fought and won a victory over her husband, who was a thief, before she became a paribbajika.
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Self-conquest is the best</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>104</Nr>
	  <Txt>Self-conquest is, indeed, far greater than the conquest of all other folk; neither a god nor a gandhabba, nor Mara with Brahma, can win back the victory of such a person who is self-subdued and ever lives in restraint.</Txt>
	</Par>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>105</Nr>
	  <Txt>Self-conquest is, indeed, far greater than the conquest of all other folk; neither a god nor a gandhabba, nor Mara with Brahma, can win back the victory of such a person who is self-subdued and ever lives in restraint.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>the Brahmin Anatthapucchaka</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verses (104) and (105) of this book, with reference to Anatthapucchaka, a brahmin.
On one occasion, a Brahmin by the name of Anatthapucchaka came to the Buddha and said to him, "Venerable Sir, I think that you know only the practices that are beneficial and not the practices that are unbeneficial." To him, the Buddha answered that he also knew the practices which were unbeneficial and harmful. Then the Buddha enumerated six practices which cause dissipation of wealth; they are: (1) sleeping until the sun has risen, (2) habitual idleness, (3) cruelty, (4) indulgence in intoxicants which causes drunkenness and negligence, (5) sauntering alone in streets at unearthly hours, and (6) sexual misconduct.
Further, the Buddha asked the brahmin how he earned his living, and the brahmin replied that he earned his living by playing dice, i.e., by gambling. Next, the Buddha asked him whether he won or lost. When the brahmin answered that he sometimes lost and sometimes won, the Buddha said to him, "To win in a game of dice is nothing compared to a victory over moral defilements."
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>None can turn into defeat self-victory</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>106</Nr>
	  <Txt>Though month after month with a thousand, one should make an offering for a hundred years, yet, if, only for a moment, one should honour (a Saint) who has perfected himself - that honour is, indeed, better than a century of sacrifice.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Thera Sariputta's Uncle</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Veluvana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (106) of this book, with reference to a brahmin, who was the maternal uncle of Thera Sariputta.
On one occasion, Thera Sariputta asked his uncle the brahmin whether he was doing any meritorious deeds. The brahmin answered that he was making offerings to the value of one thousand Kahapanas every month to the Nigantha ascetics, hoping to get to the Brahma world in his next existence. Thera Sariputta then explained to him that his teachers had given him false hopes and that they themselves did not know the way to the Brahma world. So saying, he took his uncle the brahmin to the Buddha, and requested the Buddha to expound the Dhamma, which would surely take one to the Brahma world.
The Buddha said to the brahmin, "Brahmin, an offering of a spoonful of alms-food to a monk would be much better than your present offering of one thousand Kahapanas to your teachers."
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Honour the worthy</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>107</Nr>
	  <Txt>Though, for a century a man should tend the (sacred) fire in the forest, yet, if, only for a moment, he should honour (a Saint) who has perfected himself - that honour is, indeed, better than a century of fire-sacrifice.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Thera Sariputta's Nephew</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Veluvana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (107) of this book, with reference to Thera Sariputta's nephew.
On one occasion, Thera Sariputta asked his nephew, a brahmin, whether he was doing any meritorious deeds. His nephew answered that he had been sacrificing a goat in fire-worship every month, hoping to get to the Brahma world in his next existence. Thera Sariputta then explained to him that his teachers had given him false hopes and that they themselves did not know the way to the Brahma world.
Then he took his nephew the young brahmin to the Buddha. There, the Buddha taught him the Dhamma that would lead one to the Brahmin world and said to the brahmin, "Young brahmin, paying homage to the monks for a moment would be far better than making sacrifices in fire-worship for a hundred years."
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Honour the pure</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>108</Nr>
	  <Txt>In this world whatever gift or alms a person seeking merit should offer for a year, all that is not worth a single quarter of the reverence towards the Upright which is excellent.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Thera Sariputta's Friend</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Veluvana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (108) of this book, with reference to a friend of Thera Sariputta.
On one occasion Thera Sariputta asked his friend, a brahmin, whether he was doing any meritorious deeds and he replied that he had been making sacrificial offerings on a big scale, hoping to get to the Brahma world in his next existence. Thera Sariputta told him that his teachers had given him false hopes and that they themselves did not know the way to the Brahma world. Then he took his friend to the Buddha, who showed him the way to the Brahma world. To the friend of Thera Sariputta, the Buddha said, "Brahmin, worshipping the Noble Ones (Ariyas) only for a moment is better than making sacrificial offerings, great and small, throughout the year."
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Honour the worthy</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>109</Nr>
	  <Txt>For one who is in the habit of constantly honouring and respecting the elders, four blessings increase - age, beauty, bliss, and strength.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Ayuvaddhanakumara</Title>
	<Txt>While residing in a village monastery near Dighalanghika, the Buddha uttered Verse (109) of this book, with reference to Ayuvaddhanakumara.
Once, there were two hermits who fixed together practising religious austerities (tapacaranam) for forty eight years. Later, one of the two left the hermit life and got married. After a son was born, the family visited the old hermit and paid obeisance to him. To the parents the hermit said, "May you live long," but he said nothing to the child. The parents were puzzled and asked the hermit the reason for his silence. The hermit told them that the child would live only seven more days and that he did not know how to prevent his death, but Gotama Buddha might know how to do it.
So the parents took the child to the Buddha; when they paid obeisance to the Buddha, he also said, "May you live long" to the parents only and not to the child. The Buddha also predicted the impending death of the child. To prevent his death, the parents were told to build a pavilion at the entrance to the house, and put the child on a couch in the pavilion. Then some monks were sent there to recite the parittas* for seven days. On the seventh day the Buddha himself came to that pavilion; the devas from all over the universe also came. At that time the ogre Avaruddhaka was at the entrance, waiting for a chance to take the child away. But as more powerful devas arrived the ogre had to step back and make room for them so that he had to stay at a place two yojanas away from the child. That whole night, recitation of parittas continued, thus protecting the child. The next day, the child was taken up from the couch and made to pay obeisance to the Buddha. This time, the Buddha said, "May you live long" to the child. When asked how long the child would live, the Buddha replied that he would live up to one hundred and twenty years. So the child was named Ayuvaddhana.
When the child grew up, he went about the country with a company of five hundred fellow devotees. One day, they came to the Jetavana monastery, and the monks, recognizing him, asked the Buddha, "For beings, is there any means of gaining longevity?" To this question the Buddha answered, "By respecting and honouring the elders and those who are wise and virtuous, one would gain not only longevity, but also beauty, happiness and strength."
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Honour the worthy</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>110</Nr>
	  <Txt>Though one should live a hundred years, immoral and uncontrolled, yet better, indeed, is a single day's life of one who is moral and meditative.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Samanera Samkicca</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (110) of this book, with reference to Samanera Samkicca.
On one occasion, thirty monks each took a subject of meditation from the Buddha and left for a large village, one hundred and twenty yojanas away from Sāvatthī. At that time, five hundred robbers were staying in a thick jungle, and they wanted to make an offering of human flesh and blood to the guardian spirits of the forest. So they came to the village monastery and demanded that one of the monks be given up to them for sacrifice to the guardian spirits. From the eldest to the youngest, each one of the monks volunteered to go. With the monks, there was also a young samanera by the name of Samkicca, who was sent along with them by Thera Sariputta. This samanera was only seven years old, but had already attained arahatship. Samkicca said that Thera Sariputta, his teacher, knowing this danger in advance, had purposely sent him to accompany the monks, and that he should be the one to go with the robbers. So saying, he went along with the robbers. The monks felt very bad for having let the young samanera go. The robbers made preparations for the sacrifice; when everything was ready, their leader came to the samanera, who was then seated, with his mind fixed on jhana collectedness. The leader of the robbers lifted his sword and struck hard at the young samanera, but the blade of the sword curled up without cutting the flesh. He straightened up the blade and struck again; this time, it bent upwards right up to the hilt without harming the samanera. Seeing this strange happening, the leader of the robbers dropped his sword, knelt at the feet of the samanera and asked his pardon. All the five hundred robbers were amazed and terror-stricken; they repented and asked permission from Samkicca to become monks. He complied with their request.
The young samanera accompanied by five hundred new monks returned to the village monastery and the thirty monks felt very much relieved and happy on seeing him. Then Samkicca and the five hundred monks continued on their way to pay respect to Thera Sariputta, his teacher, at the Jetavana monastery. After seeing Thera Sariputta they went to pay homage to the Buddha. When told what had happened, the Buddha said, "Monks, if you rob or steal and commit all sorts of evil deeds, your life would be useless, even if you were to live a hundred years. Living a virtuous life even for a single day is much better than a hundred years of a life of depravity.
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Live a virtuous life</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>111</Nr>
	  <Txt>Though one should live a hundred years without wisdom and control, yet better, indeed, is a single day's life of one who is wise and meditative.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Khanu-Kondanna</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (111) of this book, with reference to Khanu Kondanna.
Thera Kondanna, after taking a subject of meditation from the Buddha, went into the jungle to practise meditation and there attained arahatship. Coming back to pay homage to the Buddha, he stopped on the way because he was very tired. He sat on a large stone-slab, his mind fixed in jhana collectedness. At that moment five hundred robbers after looting a large village came to the place where the thera was. Taking him for a tree stump they put their bundles of loot all over and around the body of the thera. When day broke they realized that what they took to be a tree stump was, in fact, a living being. Then again, they thought it was an ogre and ran away in fright.
The thera revealed to them that he was only a monk and not an ogre and told them not to get frightened. The robbers were awed by his words, and asked his pardon for having wronged him. Soon after wards, all the robbers requested the thera to admit them into the Order. From that time, Thera Kondanna came to be known as "Khanu Kondanna" (tree-stump Kondanna)
The thera accompanied by the new monks went to the Buddha and told him all that had happened. To them the Buddha said, "To live for a hundred years in ignorance, doing foolish things, is useless; now that you have seen the Truth and have become wise, your life of one day as a wise man is much more worthwhile."
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Increase your wisdom</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>112</Nr>
	  <Txt>Though one should live a hundred years idle and inactive yet better, indeed, is a single day's life of one who makes an intense effort.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Thera Sappadasa</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (112) of this book, with reference to Thera Sappadasa.
Once a monk was not feeling happy with the life of a monk; at the same time he felt that it would be improper and humiliating for him to return to the life of a householder. So he thought it would be better to die. So thinking, on one occasion, he put his hand into a pot where there was a snake but the snake did not bite him. This was because in a past existence the snake was a slave and the monk was his master. Because of this incident the monk was known as Thera Sappadasa. On another occasion, Thera Sappadasa took a razor to cut his throat; but as he placed the razor on his throat he reflected on the purity of his morality practice throughout his life as a monk and his whole body was suffused with delightful satisfaction (piti) and bliss (sukha). Then detaching himself from piti, he directed his mind to the development of Insight Knowledge and soon attained arahatship, and he returned to the monastery.
On arrival at the monastery, other monks asked him where he had been and why he took the knife along with him. When he told them about his intention to take his life, they asked him why he did not do so. He answered, "I originally intended to cut my throat with this knife, but I have now cut off all moral defilements with the knife of Insight Knowledge." The monks did not believe him; so they went to the Buddha and asked. "Venerable Sir, this monk claims, that he has attained arahatship as he was putting the knife to his throat to kill himself. Is it possible to attain Arahatta Magga within such a short time?" To them the Buddha said, "Monks! Yes, it is possible; for one who is zealous and strenuous in the practice of Tranquillity and Insight Development, arahatship can be gained in an instant. As the monk walks in meditation, he can attain arahatship even before his raised foot touches the ground."
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Practice meditation</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>113</Nr>
	  <Txt>Though one should live a hundred years without comprehending how all things rise and pass away, yet better, indeed, is a single day's life of one who comprehends how all things rise and pass away.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Theri Patacara</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (113) of this book, with reference to Patacara.
Patacara was the daughter of a rich man from Sāvatthī. She was very beautiful and was guarded very strictly by her parents. But one day, she eloped with a young male attendant of the family and went to live in a village, as a poor man's wife. In due course she became pregnant and as the time for confinement drew near, she asked permission from her husband to return to her parents in Sāvatthī, but her husband discouraged her. So, one day, while her husband was away, she set out for the home of her parents. Her husband followed her and caught up with her on the way and pleaded with her to return with him; but she refused. It so happened that as her time was drawing so near, she had to give birth to a son in one of the bushes. After the birth of her son she returned home with her husband.
Then, she was again with child and as the time for confinement drew nears taking her son with her, she again set out for the home of her parents in Sāvatthī. Her husband followed her and caught up with her on the way; but her time for delivery was coming on very fast and it was also raining hard. The husband looked for a suitable place for confinement and while he was clearing a little patch of land, he was bitten by a poisonous snake, and died instantaneously. Patacara waited for her husband, and while waiting for his return she gave birth to her second son. In the morning, she searched for her husband, but only found his dead body. Saying to herself that her husband died on account of her, she continued on her way to her parents.
Because it had rained incessantly the whole night, the river Aciravati was in spate; so it was not possible for her to cross the river carrying both her sons. Leaving the elder boy on this side of the river, she crossed the stream with her day-old son and left him on the other bank. She then came back for the elder boy. While she was still in the middle of the river, a large hawk hovered over the younger child taking it for a piece of meat. She shouted to frighten away the bird, but it was all in vain; the child was carried away by the hawk. Meanwhile, the elder boy heard his mother shouting from the middle of the stream and thought she was calling out to him to come to her. So he entered the stream to go to his mother, and was carried away by the strong current. Thus, Patacara lost her two sons as well as her husband.
So she wept and lamented loudly, "A son is carried away by a hawk, another son is carried away by the current, my husband is also dead, bitten by a poisonous snake!" Then, she saw a man from Sāvatthī and she tearfully asked after her parents. The man replied that due to a violent storm in Sāvatthī the previous night, the house of her parents had fallen down and that both her parents together with her three brothers, had died, and had been cremated on one funeral pyre. On hearing this tragic news, Patacara went stark mad. She did not even notice that her clothes had fallen off from her and that she was half-naked. She went about the streets, shouting out her woes.
While the Buddha was giving a discourse at the Jetavana monastery, he saw Patacara at a distance; so he willed that she should come to the congregation. The crowd seeing her coming tried to stop her, saying "Don't let the mad woman come in." But the Buddha told them not to prevent her coming in. When Patacara was close enough to hear him, he told her to be careful and to keep calm. Then, she realized that she did not have her skirt on and shamefacedly sat down. Someone gave her a piece of cloth and she wrapped herself up in it. She then told the Buddha how she had lost her sons, her husband, her brothers and her parents.
The Buddha said to her, "Patacara, have no fear; you have now come to one who can protect you and guide you. Throughout this round of existences (samsara), the amount of tears you have shed on account of the death of your sons, husbands, parents and brothers is voluminous; it is even more than the waters of the four oceans." Thus the Buddha expounded to her the Anamatagga Sutta, which dealt with countless existences, and she felt relieved. Then, the Buddha added that one should not think too much about those who were gone, but that one should purify oneself and strive to realize Nibbāna. On hearing this exhortation from the Buddha, Patacara attained Sotapatti Fruition.
Then, Patacara became a bhikkhuni. One day, she was cleaning her feet with water from a water-pot. As she poured the water for the first time, it flowed only a short distance and disappeared; then she poured for the second time and the water went a little farther, but the water she poured for the third time went the farthest. As she looked at the flow and the disappearance of water poured cut successively for three times, she came to perceive clearly the three stages in the life of beings. The Buddha seeing her through supernormal power from the Jetavana monastery sent forth his radiance and appeared to her in person. He then said to her, "Patacara, you are now on the right track, and you now have the true perception of the aggregates (khandhas). One who does not perceive the impermanence, unsatisfactoriness and insubstantiality of the aggregates is useless, even if he were to live for a hundred years.
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Increase your wisdom</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>114</Nr>
	  <Txt>Though one should live a hundred years without seeing the Deathless State, yet better, indeed, is a single day's life of one who sees the Deathless State.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Theri Kisagotami</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, thc Buddha uttered Verse (114) of this book, with reference to Kisagotami.
Kisagotami was the daughter of a rich man from Sāvatthī; she was known as Kisagotami because of her slim body. Kisagotami was married to a rich young man and a son was born to them. The boy died when he was just a toddler and Kisagotami was stricken with grief. Carrying the dead body of her son, she went about asking for medicine that would restore her son to life from everyone she happened to meet. People began to think that she had gone mad. But a wise man seeing her condition thought that he should be of some help to her. So, he said to her, "The Buddha is the person you should approach, he has the medicine you want; go to him." Thus, she went to the Buddha and asked him to give her the medicine that would restore her dead son to life.
The Buddha told her to get some mustard seeds from a house where there had been no death. Carrying her dead child in her bosom. Kisagotami went from house to house, with the request for some mustard seeds. Everyone was willing to help her, but she could not find a single house where death had not occurred. Then, she realized that hers was not the only family that had faced death and that there were more people dead than living. As soon as she realized this, her attitude towards her dead son changed; she was no longer attached to the dead body of her son.
She left the corpse in the jungle and returned to the Buddha and reported that she could find no house where death had not occurred. Then the Buddha said,"Gotami, you thought that you were the only one who had lost a son. As you have now realized, death comes to all beings; before their desires are satiated death takes them away." On hearing this, Kisagotami fully realized the impermanence, unsatisfactoriness and insubstantiality of the aggregates and attained Sotapatti Fruition.
Soon afterwards, Kisagotami became a bhikkhuni. One day, as she was lighting the lamps she saw the flames flaring up and dying out, and suddenly she clearly perceived the arising and the perishing of beings. The Buddha, through supernormal power, saw her from his monastery, and sent forth his radiance and appeared to her in person. Kisagotami was told to continue meditating on the impermanent nature of all beings and to strive hard to realize Nibbāna.
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Work towards awakening</Summary>
    </Verse>
    <Verse>
      <Paragraphs>
	<Par>
	  <Nr>115</Nr>
	  <Txt>Though one should live a hundred years not seeing the Truth Sublime, yet better, indeed, is a single day's life of one who sees the Truth Sublime.</Txt>
	</Par>
      </Paragraphs>
      <Story>
	<Title>Theri Bahuputtika</Title>
	<Txt>While residing at the Jetavana monastery, the Buddha uttered Verse (115) of this book, with reference to Bahuputtika, a mother of many children.
Once in Sāvatthī, there lived a couple, with their seven sons and seven daughters. All the children got married and the family was doing quite well. Then, the father died and the mother kept all the property without giving anything to the children. Her sons and daughters wanted the inheritance, so they said, to their mother, "What benefit do we get from our property? Can't we make it multiply? Can't we look after our mother?" They said such things again and again so their mother thought that her children would look after her, and she finally divided up the property without leaving anything for herself.
After the division of the property, she first went to stay with her eldest son, but her daughter-in-law complained and said, "She has come and stayed with us, as if she has given us two shares!", and such other things. So, Bahuputtika went to stay with her second son, and the same things were said. Thus, she went from one son to another, from one daughter to the next; but none of them was willing to take her on for a long stretch of time and none paid her due respect.
The old lady was hurt and felt bitter against her children; she left her family and became a bhikkhuni. Because she was a mother of many children she came to he known as Bahuputtika. Bahuputika realized that she became a bhikkhuni only in her old age and that she must not be negligent, but must make use of the remaining period of her life to the utmost. So, for the whole night, she meditated on the Dhamma taught by the Buddha. The Buddha seeing her from the Jetavana monastery, through supernormal power, sent forth the radiance and appeared seated in front of her. Then the Buddha said to her, "The life of one who does not practise the Dhamma taught by me is useless, even if he were to live for a hundred years."
</Txt>
      </Story>
      <Summary>Learn the Dhamma</Summary>
    </Verse>
  </Verses>
</Chapter>
